<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The odious, despicable, and dreadfull condition of a drunkard, drawn to the life to deterre others, and cause them to decline the wayes of death, or, A hopefull way to cure drunkennesse (the root of all evill, and rot of all good) in such as are not (by long custome) past cure : composed, and published for their good, who (not for want of ignorance) prinde themselves in drunken good-fellowship : which probably may open their eies, as the tasting of honey did Jonathan, and cause them to say as the governour to the bridegroome, John 2.10, The good wine was kept back untill now / by Junius Florilegus.</title>
            <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97251</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y167A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43834</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">42475299</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 42475299</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151474</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97251)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151474)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2260:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The odious, despicable, and dreadfull condition of a drunkard, drawn to the life to deterre others, and cause them to decline the wayes of death, or, A hopefull way to cure drunkennesse (the root of all evill, and rot of all good) in such as are not (by long custome) past cure : composed, and published for their good, who (not for want of ignorance) prinde themselves in drunken good-fellowship : which probably may open their eies, as the tasting of honey did Jonathan, and cause them to say as the governour to the bridegroome, John 2.10, The good wine was kept back untill now / by Junius Florilegus.</title>
                  <author>Younge, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Cotes, and are to be sold by Nicholas Bourne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, worn, and tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alcoholism --  Moral and ethical aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Odious, Deſpicable, and Dreadfull condition of a <hi>Drunkard;</hi> drawne to the <hi>Life:</hi> to deterre others, and cauſe them to decline the wayes of <hi>Death.</hi> OR A hopefull way to cure Drunkenneſſe, (the root of all evill, and rot of all good) in ſuch as are not (by long cuſtome) paſt cure. Compoſed, and Publiſhed for their good; who (not for want of Ignorance) pride themſelves in drunken good-fellowſhip. Which probably may open their eies, as the taſting of Hony did <hi>Jonathans;</hi> and cauſe them to ſay as the Governour to the Bridegroome, John 2.10. <hi>The good wine was kept backe untill now. By Junius Florilegus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. Cotes,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Nicholas Bourne</hi> at the South entrance of the <hi>Royall Exchange,</hi> 1649.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="testimonial">
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>What ſome Reverend Divines deem of the DRUNKARDS CHARACTER, out of which <hi>Quiver</hi> this <hi>Arrow</hi> is drawne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving adviſedly read over and peruſed a <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> bearing the name of <hi>R. Junius,</hi> which for ſome conſiderations came formerly abroad, vailed under the Title of <hi>The Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards Character,</hi> and <hi>Compleat Armour againſt evill ſociety;</hi> we finde it to be for generality of diſcourſe; as a large <hi>Map</hi> of moſt mens thoughts, words, and actions. For, beſides that foule ſinne of Drunkenneſs, and many other vices, which commonly accompany the ſame, very pithily, orderly, and elegantly, with much both ſinew ous ſtrength of Argument and variety of gracefull and delightfull illuſtrations therein diſcovered, and dealt with; we have further obſerved in it, ſuch other ſubject matter, concerning the knowledge, beleefe, and life, of common Proteſtants, what too frequently it is, and what in truth it ought to be, (that it may anſwer to their profeſsion, and the <hi>Title</hi> that they beare) wherein alſo all manner
<pb facs="tcp:151474:5"/>of <hi>Chriſtian Graces</hi> are illuſtrate, and ſet out by the foul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and deformity of their oppoſite <hi>vices;</hi> that for the variety of uſefull matter therein handled, together with the perſpicuous, pleaſant, and yet powerfull manner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsion; we conceive that it may very much conduce, both as a <hi>Glaſſe</hi> for perſons generally, to ſee the face of their owne heart in; and as a <hi>Trumpet</hi> alowd ſounding, to ſummon ſinners to repentance: beſides that unto young Scholars alſo it may be not unuſefull, as an help to furniſh them with matter concerning thoſe common heads of <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue</hi> and <hi>Vice,</hi> and moſt of the uſuall Subjects aſwel of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity</hi> as <hi>Morality:</hi> But likewiſe touching the manifold <hi>ſleights</hi> and <hi>advantages</hi> of <hi>Satan</hi> and wicked men, in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſinne, and drawing to perdition. In regard where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of we deeme it very worthy the reprinting with a fuller and further promiſing <hi>Title.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Gataker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Downame.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Walker.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charles Ofspring.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Samuell Bolton.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Richard Vines.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Cranford.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>John Crodacott.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Xperience teaches that no one thing (be it the Violet) will pleaſe every one. That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more eaſie, then to finde a colour of exceptions. That mens cenſures are as various as their palats; that ſome are as deeply in love with vice, as others are with vertue. That croſſed wickedneſs proves deſperate; and in ſtead of yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, ſeeks for revenge of its own ſins, upon others up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſs.</p>
            <p>The Prophet alſo tells me my wages before hand, <hi>Come let us ſmite him with the Tongue, Jer.</hi> 18.18. And <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> more expreſly, <hi>He that reproveth a ſcorner, purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to himſelfe ſhame, and hee that rebuketh the wicked, getteth himſelfe a blot, Prov.</hi> 9.7. Shall I then make my ſelf the ſubject of every opinion wiſe and weak? Yes, I had rather hazard the cenſure of ſome, then hinder the good of others. Yea admit, in ſtead of their tongues, they ſhould uſe their ſwords, (the caſe of <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> for reproving of <hi>Herod</hi>) Gods glory we are bound to redeeme, with our own lives.</p>
            <p>Againe, if I do ill, no plea can warrant me; if well, I cannot bee diſcouraged with any cenſures. Nevertheleſs, that I may ſatisfie all honeſt minds, (leſt they alſo ſhould wreſt my words beyond the level of my thoughts) that I may free my Reader and my ſelfe from miſtaking, and being miſtaken, (becauſe it is not enough to find our own hearts clear, except alſo we clear our names, and the
<pb facs="tcp:151474:6"/>conſciences of others) I will remove ſome rubs, level the ground, and pave a way to our enſuing matter.</p>
            <p>What will be alledged againſt this diſcourſe, my ſelfe (though I am no <hi>Antevorta</hi>) foreſees; yea I could raiſe to their hand, all their objections, and as eaſily anſwer them. But two only deſerve anſwering, the reſt are not worth the repeating.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſome will aske why in this Treatiſe of all the reſt, my <hi>expreſsions</hi> are ſo light, and my <hi>compariſons</hi> ſo home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? And to theſe my anſwer is; that I may kill <hi>Goliah</hi> with his owne Sword; diſpute with <hi>Drunkards</hi> in their owne Dialect: For either they underſtand no other lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage; or if ſo, they finde no more reliſh or ſweetneſſe in ſolid Divinity, then in the white of an Egge: becauſe their palats are brought out of taſte by the world, and luſts of the fleſh.</p>
            <p>Beſides, this ſubject is leſſe ſerious then any of the reſt; And it is not poſſible with grave and modeſt words, to expreſſe, and paint out their light, vaine, and laſcivious language and behaviour.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if any that are addicted to this vice, (for whoſe gain I am content to loſe) ſhall ask why I am ſo bitter? I would deſire them (though in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> yea in common e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity I might enjoine them) to conſider theſe ſix enſuing circumſtances; and then they will pardon my juſt vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, and only blame the foulneſſe of this ſin.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that the medicine is but fitted to the diſeaſe, the wedge but proportioned to the timber, which could not be avoided; for the harder, and more knotty our hearts are, the harder and ſtronger muſt be the blowes and wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges that muſt rive them. And nothing but a <hi>Diamond</hi> will cut a <hi>Diamond.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:6"/>
            <p>Secondly, without a diſcovery of our diſeaſe, there can be no recovery of our health. The ſight of our filthineſſe, is the firſt ſtep toward cleanneſſe. And how many may bleſſe the time, that ever they were plainly dealt withall? witneſſe <hi>Antiochus,</hi> and <hi>Antoninus</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> S. <hi>Paul Acts</hi> 9.3, to 8. and thoſe murtherers of the <hi>Lord of life, Acts</hi> 2.36, to 42.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, they ſhould conſider, that I fight not againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but againſt their ſinnes; not with them, but againſt their enemies for them; knowing that unleſſe thoſe dye, they cannot live.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it would alſo be conſidered, that the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> is not to be blamed for the paine of his <hi>Patient;</hi> but the <hi>diſeaſe:</hi> not the <hi>Chirurgeon,</hi> but the <hi>wound:</hi> which he endeavours by all meanes to cure. And wounds more <hi>dangerous,</hi> require more <hi>dolorous</hi> plaiſters: Yea if Phyſick bee not ſtrong enough to purge out the diſeaſe, it increaſeth it. Which makes a good <hi>Phyſitian</hi> give <hi>ſharpe</hi> medicines and <hi>bitter</hi> potions, that he may make ſhort diſeaſes, and procure ſound health. And for the moſt part, thoſe things that are leaſt pleaſing, are moſt whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, let them conſider, that all is done in love, and for their good. And even thoſe pils which are moſt bitter, will downe, when, they are wrapt up in love, and for our healths. Yea wee will ſuffer inciſions, even the opening of our veines, and the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of our bloud, when we know it is done in love, and to ſave our lives.</p>
            <p>Yea, neither the <hi>Phyſitian</hi> nor <hi>Chirurgeon</hi> heales us without paine; and yet we both reward and thanke them. Which is our very caſe; for even thoſe invectives that are moſt keen, and ſharpe, do but reſemble <hi>Jonathans Arrowes,</hi> which were not ſhot to hurt <hi>David,</hi> but to give him warning, and to occaſion his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape from <hi>Sauls</hi> fury. Whereas their ſcoffes and ſlaunders againſt us, that <hi>will not runne with them to the ſame exceſſe of riot;</hi> may fitly be compared to <hi>Sanls ſpeare,</hi> which was darted on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not to hurt onely, but to murther and to deſtroy.</p>
            <p>Yea let them be read without prejudice, and (by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing)
<pb facs="tcp:151474:7"/>they ſhall be unto them, as <hi>Davids harpe</hi> was to <hi>Saul,</hi> which frighted away the evill ſpirit from him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.23. Or as the <hi>Cocks crowing</hi> to <hi>Peter,</hi> which occaſioned his repentance, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.74, 75. Or as thoſe Meſſengers to <hi>Lot,</hi> that came to fetch him out of <hi>Sodome,</hi> that he might not feele the fire and brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone which followed. <hi>Gen.</hi> 19. Yea as the Angel was 10 <hi>Peter,</hi> that opened the Iron gates, looſed his bands, brought him out of priſon, and delivered him from the thraldom of his enemies. <hi>Acts</hi> 12. <hi>Theſe things have I ſaid, that they may be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixtly, let them conſider, that if theſe judgements bee ſo dreadfull to heare: how terrible will they be to feel? The <hi>Law</hi> (<hi>Waſpe</hi>-like) ſtings ſhrewdly, but <hi>Satan</hi> that <hi>Hornet</hi> will ſting worſe a great deale: but if men will be warned by the former, (as who would not rather be converted then confounded? or who had not rather a Booke or Sermon ſhould awaken him, then fire and brimſtone?) they may prevent the latter.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, (though there needs neither reaſons to be given, nor excuſe, or apology to be made, where the Word is our warrant, and the glory of God our aime,) moſt humbly beſeeching <hi>God,</hi> who only hath the key of the heart, and can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the eyes of theſe poore ſoules, to ſee the miſerable ſlavery and danger they are in: to bleſſe this weake meanes preſcribed for their recovery, and others warning. I leave its ſucceſſe to Him, its uſe to the world; and referre my ſelfe to the honeſt and intelligent Readers judgement: as for others, let them ſmite me being abſent I care not; for their diſpraiſe is a mans honor, their praiſe his diſhonour.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. F.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151474:7"/>
            <head>The Odious, Deſpicable, and Dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Condition of a <hi>Drunkard,</hi> drawne to the LIFE: to deterre others, and cauſe them to decline the wayes of DEATH.</head>
            <p>§ 1.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
               <hi>Drunkard</hi> (and I take him for ſuch, that drinkes more for luſt, or pride, or covetouſneſſe, or feare, or good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or to drive away time, or to ſtill conſcience, then for thirſt;) being one of thoſe Creatures, which <hi>God</hi> never made in the <hi>Creation:</hi> (like that ſpoken of <hi>Gen.</hi> 36.24.) is halfe a Man, halfe a Beaſt; or one that was borne a Man, lives a Beaſt; or one that hath a Beſtiall heart in a Caſe of humane fleſh. For through cuſtome of ſinne, and a juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God upon it, he hath his heart changed from mans nature, and a beaſts heart given him in the ſtead; as it fared with <hi>Nebuchadnezzar, Dan.</hi> 4.16.</p>
            <p>Whereas other ſinnes deprive a man of <hi>Gods</hi> Image, this deprives him of mans; and for the preſent, robs him of himſelfe; leaving him neither the uſe of reaſon, nor ſpeech, without which he is no better then a Beaſt. Nor does hee ſo much ſurpaſſe a Beaſt in his ſhape, as he out-ſtrips a Beaſt in beaſtlineſſe, as <hi>Hermes</hi> well obſerves. Yea reckon up all the brutiſh conditions, obſerveable in other Beaſts; and you ſhall finde every of them to meet in a Drunkard, as <hi>Rivers</hi> in the <hi>Sea.</hi> As produce the very worſt qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, in the very worſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Beaſts, and this Beaſt will match them all, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being matcht by any; as for inſtance.</p>
            <p>In one beaſtly quality, he is like the <hi>Jerffe,</hi> a Beaſt in the North parts of <hi>Swetia,</hi> whoſe property (as <hi>Geſner</hi> out of <hi>Olaus Magnus</hi> relates) is, when he hath killed his prey, or found ſome carkaſſe, to fall a devouring the ſame, and never leave feeding, untill his belly bee puffed up, and ſtrouteth like a Bag-pipe, and then not being able to hold any more, he goeth betweene two narrow Trees, and ſtraineth out backward what he hath eaten; and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made empty, returneth againe to the Carkaſſe and filleth himſelfe as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and then ſtraineth it out the ſecond time; and ſo continueth filling and emptying himſelfe, untill he hath devoured all; which being conſumed he hunteth after more; and this is the courſe of his whole life. In ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther particular, he is like the <hi>Aſſes</hi> of <hi>Thuſcia:</hi> who when they have fed upon
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:151474:8"/>
               <hi>Hemlocks,</hi> ſleepe ſo ſoundly, that they ſeeme to be dead, in ſo much that the Country men many times, more then flea off halfe their skins, before they will awake. And ſo of the reſt, which I can but name; for in heart he is a <hi>Swine;</hi> in head a <hi>Cephalus;</hi> in tongue an <hi>Aſpe;</hi> in belly a <hi>Lumpe;</hi> in appetite a <hi>Leech;</hi> in ſloath an <hi>Ignavus;</hi> a <hi>Goat</hi> for luſt; a <hi>Siren</hi> for flattery; a <hi>Hiena</hi> for ſubtilty; a <hi>Panther</hi> for cruelty; in envying a <hi>Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liske;</hi> in antipathy to all good, a <hi>Lexus;</hi> in hindering others from good, a <hi>Remora;</hi> in life a <hi>Salamander;</hi> in conſcience an <hi>Oſtrich,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And what ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> to ſuch an one? ſhall I think thee a <hi>Man,</hi> when thou haſt all the qualities of a <hi>Beaſt?</hi> ſwilleſt like a <hi>Swine?</hi> kickeſt like an Aſſe? neigheſt after women like a <hi>Horſe?</hi> rageſt in luſt like a <hi>Bull?</hi> rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt like a <hi>Beare?</hi> ſtingeſt like a <hi>Scorpion?</hi> rakeſt like a <hi>Wolfe?</hi> art as fierce as a <hi>Tyger?</hi> as ſubtill as a <hi>Fox?</hi> as impudent, and ſhameleſſe as a <hi>Dog?</hi> no, I ſee nothing of Man in thee, ſave thy ſhape: and that affrights me the more, when I ſee a <hi>Beaſt</hi> in the likeneſſe of a <hi>Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 2. And yet poore ſoules, they like their condition ſo well, that they would not change upon any termes; for as thoſe <hi>Beaſts</hi> ſpoken of by <hi>Plutarch,</hi> renounced the benefit of <hi>Circes</hi> grant, and deſired <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> that hee would not preſſe them with the reaccepting of reaſon; ſo call Drunkards from their brutiſh ſenſuality, they will reject the offer: what, make them men? no, they thanke you as much as if you did, they had rather be beaſts ſtill. As the have no reaſon, ſo they will heare none. Yea, they are more brutiſh then thoſe beaſts: for whereas Chriſt by us would reconcile them to God; as <hi>Joab</hi> did <hi>Abſalom</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> by the woman of <hi>Tekoah:</hi> they cry <hi>we come to torment them.</hi> Their caſe being like his in the Goſpell, that called himſelfe <hi>Legion:</hi> who having beene poſſeſt with Devils a long time, was at length very loath to part with his gueſts. Yea he thought himſelfe tormented, when Chriſt came to caſt out them, and ſave him. <hi>Marke</hi> 1.24. <hi>Luke</hi> 8.28. And the reaſon is, Drunkenneſſe beſtiates the <hi>heart,</hi> and ſpoiles the <hi>braine,</hi> overthrowes the <hi>faculties</hi> and <hi>organs</hi> of repentance, and reſolution; turnes <hi>reaſon</hi> into exile, and poiſoneth the very ſoule of a man: As how doth it damme up the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>ſpirits</hi> with mud? how doth it infatuate the <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding?</hi> blinde the <hi>judgement,</hi> pervert the <hi>will,</hi> and corrupt all the <hi>affections?</hi> how doth it ſurprize the <hi>thoughts,</hi> entrap the <hi>deſires,</hi> and bring all the <hi>powers</hi> and <hi>faculties</hi> of the ſoule out of order? as experience proves and the <hi>Word</hi> alſo; which informes us, that the <hi>exceſſe of wine takes away the heart;</hi> makes men <hi>mad, feeliſh,</hi> and <hi>out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>agious;</hi> makes them forget God and his Lawes. <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.1. and 31.3, 4, 5. Yea that it makes men utterly to fall away from God, untill they are uncapable of returning, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.35. <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.11, 12. and 56.12. For by this ſinne the <hi>heart</hi> is hardened, the <hi>ſpirit</hi> quenched, and the <hi>body of ſinne</hi> with all its <hi>luſts</hi> ſo ſtrengthened, that it keeps them in finall impenitency, <hi>Eſay</hi> 22.12, 13, 14. and 28.7, 8. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.13, 14. <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.21. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.18. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.11. Yea the ſoule by it, is made <hi>like a City broken downe, and without walls, Prov.</hi> 25.28. By all which it appeares, that theſe uncleane beaſts which wallow in the myre
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151474:8"/>of ſenſuality; theſe brutiſh Drunkards; which transforme themſelves through exceſſe; are even thoſe <hi>ſwing</hi> whom the <hi>Legion</hi> carries headlong to the Sea, or pit of Perdition, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.32. for otherwiſe the worſt of Beaſts will be found in a far better condition.</p>
            <p>§ 3. And indeed to give beaſts their due, it is a wrong to Beaſts to call drunkenneſſe their ſinne; for generally they are ſober, keepe within the bounds of moderation, and know when they have drunke enough. Beaſts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo keepe the prerogative of their Creation, whereas Drunkards loſe (yea ſhame) theirs. Nor do Beaſts like Drunkards, prove cruell to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves &amp;c. ſo that in many particulars a beaſt is a man, to ſuch men. But ſee this proved alſo.</p>
            <p>Such is the power of ſinne, that it made <hi>God</hi> become <hi>Man, Angels</hi> become <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vils,</hi> and <hi>Men</hi> become <hi>Beaſts.</hi> But this ſinne, this vile, and odious ſinne of drunkenneſſe, hath a more ſuperlative power; for wine bereaves the Drunkard, not onely of <hi>reaſon</hi> and <hi>ſpeech,</hi> (which two things diſtinguiſh <hi>Beaſt</hi> and <hi>Man;</hi>) but likewiſe of <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>motion,</hi> wherein beaſts excell <hi>ſtocks</hi> and <hi>ſtones.</hi> For it ſo blockifies them for the preſent, that they may fitly be compared to the Idols of the Heathen; <hi>which have eyes and ſee not, eares and heare not, tongues and ſpeake not, noſes and ſmell not,</hi> (no not their owne vomit) <hi>handes and handle not, feet and walke not,</hi> being as <hi>dead men</hi> that can neither <hi>ſit, ſtand,</hi> nor <hi>goe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 4. Or if they will (notwithſtanding all this) be taken for men; yea admit as men, they have ſome advantage above beaſts, or ſtocks: it is a miſerable advantage, that onely makes them apt to evill, yea the worſt of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils; and capable of an <hi>Hell:</hi> which is all the advantage they have; for to what men may they be likened? they are but like that <hi>lunaticke man</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.15, 16. who being <hi>ſore vexed with an evill ſpirit, fell oft-times into the fire, and oft-times into the water:</hi> whom all the <hi>Diſciples</hi> could nor cure, untill the <hi>Maſter</hi> himſelfe came. Or like that man ſpoken of <hi>Marke</hi> 5.2, to 6. who being <hi>poſſeſt with the Devil, lived amongſt the graves, and cut himſelfe with ſtones: and whom no man could tame.</hi> For they love none but baſe <hi>company,</hi> baſe <hi>places,</hi> and baſe <hi>courſes.</hi> And what does their frequent and horrible oathes but cut them deeper, then thoſe ſtones did him? Nor is <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Aaron, Ceſar</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> Miniſter of the Word, or Miniſter of the Sword, able to reſtraine or tame them.</p>
            <p>You may thinke it an hard ſaying, as the <hi>Diſciples</hi> did that of our Saviour <hi>John</hi> 6.53, to 61. But let me tell you from Gods Word, that the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>porall poſſeſſion of evill ſpirits, is not ſo rare; as the ſpirituall is rife. For no naturall man is free: as for inſtance, one hath the <hi>ſpirit of errour,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. another the <hi>ſpirit of feare,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. another the <hi>ſpirit of fornication, Hoſ.</hi> 4.12. another the <hi>ſpirit of falſhood, Mat.</hi> 24.11. another the <hi>ſpirit of blaſphemy, Rev.</hi> 2.9. and 13.1, 5, 6. another the <hi>ſpirit of ſlumber, Rom.</hi> 11.8. another the <hi>ſpirit of giddineſſe, Eſay</hi> 29.9, to 15. another the <hi>ſpirit of pride;</hi> all have the <hi>ſpirit of the world,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.12. But Drunkards for the moſt part are poſſeſt with more evill ſpirits, or Devils, then <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:151474:9"/>was, for every raigning ſinne (whereof each Drunkard hath more then a good many) is a Devill; as <hi>Auguſtine, Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Gregory,</hi> affirme.</p>
            <p>Beſides, other <hi>Scriptures</hi> make plaine that they are as truly, though ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, carried by evill ſpirits into the deeps of their knowne wickedneſſe; and conſequently are poſting Hel-wards; as ever the <hi>Gadarean Hogs were car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried</hi> by them downe the precipice <hi>into the Sea.</hi> For they are the Devils captives, at his command, and ready to do his will, as is evident by 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. Yea hee is their <hi>Father, Gen.</hi> 3.15. <hi>John</hi> 8.44. Their <hi>King, John</hi> 12.31. and 14.30. And their <hi>God,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ruling over, <hi>and working in them his pleaſure, Eph.</hi> 2.2, 3. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26. <hi>For he enters into them, and puts it into their hearts</hi> what he will have them to do; as he did formerly into <hi>Judas, John</hi> 13.2. <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira, Acts</hi> 5.3. and <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 21.1. Yea he opens their mouths and ſpeaks in, and by them as he did by the Serpent, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.1, to 6. <hi>Ahabs</hi> 400 <hi>Prophets,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.22. and <hi>Peter, Mat.</hi> 16.22, 23. ſtretcheth forth their hands, and acts by them, as he did by <hi>Herod, Acts.</hi> 12.1, 2, &amp;c. and ſtill does by <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> when they <hi>caſt the ſervants of God into priſon, Revel.</hi> 2.10. So that as <hi>Paul,</hi> being guided by the good ſpirit of <hi>God,</hi> could ſay, <hi>I live not, but Chriſt lives in me, Gal.</hi> 2.20. So may Drunkards ſay, we live not, but the Devill lives in us, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>John</hi> 14.30. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.26.</p>
            <p>Not that the mind of man is capable of a violation, either from Satan, or any elſe: nor can the wickedſt man tax any for his yeelding but himſelfe. On<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is the difference; Drunkards are driven as free Horſes; that need on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſhaking of the hand to the <hi>Taverne,</hi> to the <hi>Siues,</hi> to this or that evill company, or wicked action. Yea, they are ſo at the Devils becke, that hee needs no more but hold up his finger, (ſuggeſt the thought, or ſay the word) and 'tis done: As if hee appoint them to <hi>lye,</hi> they will lye: if he command them to <hi>deceive,</hi> they will deceive: if he bid them <hi>ſlander,</hi> they will ſlander, and that as falſly as he: if he perſwade them to <hi>revenge,</hi> to <hi>perſecute,</hi> &amp;c. they wil do it as ſpitefully and fully as he could do them himſelf. And ſo of every other ſinne. If he but ſay to them, let there be an <hi>oath,</hi> a <hi>quarrell,</hi> or the like; inſtantly they obey him. Yea, they are ſo greedy of ſinne, that were there no <hi>Devill</hi> to do his office, they would beget deſtruction on them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. If <hi>Satan</hi> ſhould not feed them with temptations, they would tempt him for them, and ſnatch their owne bane.</p>
            <p>§ 5. It's true, the Drunkard may ſeem to be in a better condition: as firſt he may have a name to live, but indeed he is <hi>dead,</hi> as S. <hi>John</hi> ſpeakes. Secondly, he may have the appearance of a man, but indeed <hi>he is a beaſt,</hi> as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſpeakes. Thirdly, he may be thought a ſound man; but indeed he is demonaicall; obſeſſed, or rather <hi>poſſeſſed with a Devill,</hi> (yea many Devils) and more miſerable then ſuch an one, becauſe it is a Devill of his owne chooſing, as <hi>Baſill</hi> ſpeakes. Yea they may moſt fitly be compared to the Devill himſelfe; whom they moſt of all reſemble,</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:151474:9"/>
            <list>
               <item>1 In Surpaſſing others in ſinne,</item>
               <item>2 In Tempting others to ſinne,</item>
               <item>3 In Drawing others to perdition.</item>
            </list>
            <p>So that it were well for them, if their condition were not worſe then the <hi>Beaſts that periſh;</hi> for their miſery is determined with their lives. Or thoſe <hi>dead images,</hi> for they can do neither good nor ill; but Drunkards are dead to all goodneſſe whatſoever; but alive, yea, very active to all wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Or ſuch as are really, and corporeally poſſeſt: for <hi>Satan</hi> carryes not ſuch but againſt their wills: as he did that <hi>man in the Goſpel</hi> into the <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> ſo uſing violence to their bodies; which makes them <hi>Satans</hi> owne ſins, and not theirs: whereas theſe are carryed willingly, and ſo become Agents in what they do; and as guilty of the ſinnes they commit, as the Tempter himſelfe, when he makes them abuſe their eyes to wantonneſs, their mouths to filthineſſe, and makes their feet ſwift to ſhed bloud. So that though their bodies are uſually free from that poſſeſſive power, yet <hi>Satan</hi> hath a farre greater power in the voluntary motions of their bodies and ſoules. So that a Drunkard is the the moſt deſpicable piece of all humanity; and not worthy to be reckoned amongſt either men, or beaſts, or any other terreſtriall creatures. Indeed in their <hi>want of reaſon,</hi> they are but transformed into <hi>beaſts;</hi> and in their <hi>want of ſenſe, and motion,</hi> but into <hi>ſtocks:</hi> but in their <hi>abuſe of reaſon,</hi> in the <hi>delight they take in ſinne,</hi> and in their <hi>miſchievous tempting others to ſinne, and drawing others to perdition,</hi> they are transformed into <hi>Devils.</hi> As will appeare when I have cut up and anatomized this <hi>Chimera,</hi> (for hitherto I have onely preſented him whole and intire) wherein that I may be briefe, let a few of his ill qualities in ſtead of many, ſerve to be rehearſed, or ſpoken of; and that ſparingly: and by them you may gueſſe at the reſidue; for as huge as the <hi>Sea</hi> is, we may taſte the <hi>ſaltneſſe</hi> thereof in a drop. Onely that you may finde it a ſhort cut, a ſure and eaſie way to make you loath drunkenneſs and love ſobriety: ſeriouſly conſider as you goe along, what a wofull ſlavery it is, to be poſſeſt with a <hi>drunken Devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 6. One baſe quality denoting the Drunkards ſlaviſh condition, and which firſt offers it ſelf, is this; Every houre ſeemes a day, and every day a month to him, which is not ſpent in a <hi>Tap-houſe;</hi> and therefore where ever his houſe is, his dwelling is at the <hi>Alehouſe,</hi> except all his mony be ſpent or hee in bed. Yea they ſeeme to have nailed their eares to a <hi>Taverne,</hi> or <hi>Alehouſe, Eſay</hi> 5.11. and to have agreed with Satan, <hi>Maſter it is good being here, let us build,</hi> &amp;c. For as <hi>they riſe up early to follow Drunkenneſſe, Eſay</hi> 5.11. ſo their firſt flight is from their beds to the <hi>Tap-houſe,</hi> or <hi>Taverne:</hi> thoſe common quagmires of all filthineſſe, where too many drawing their Patrimonies through their throats, exhauſt and laviſh out their ſubſtance; and lay plots and deviſes how to get more. For hence they fall either to open courſes of violence, or ſecret miſchiefe; till at laſt the <hi>Jaile</hi> prepares them for the <hi>Jibbet;</hi> for lightly they <hi>ſing</hi> through a <hi>red Lettis,</hi> before they <hi>cry</hi> through a <hi>Grate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is the worke of many months; do but follow them ſtep by ſtep, and you ſhall obſerve, that ſo ſoone as they are upon the Ale-bench, up comes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151474:10"/>every mans pot uncalled for, upon paine of loſing their cuſtome for a month after: which being doft are filled againe; for it is the waiters office to ſee that the <hi>pots</hi> be either alwayes <hi>full</hi> or <hi>empty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 7. Now if you will know the <hi>reaſon,</hi> why every morning their firſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice is offered to <hi>Bacchus;</hi> it is this; Firſt, they are ſicke in the morning, untill they have qualified the old heat with a new; and ſo they cure ſinne with ſinne; which yet is no other, then to heale an Ulcer by deading the fleſh: which indeed doth not make a man whole, but inſenſible of paine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by a long and deſperate cuſtome, they have turned delight, and infirmity, into neceſſity; ſo that without wine they cannot live: as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by a kind of frequency, made other mens phyſick their naturall food; whereby they bring upon themſelves ſuch an unſatiable thirſt; that they will as willingly leave to live, as leave their exceſſive drinking. For let them bee convinc't by their <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> that it will even kill them if they continue it, their anſwer ſhall be, as good be buried, as ſo much debarred of their appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tites. Neither is it poſſible, the appetites of theſe <hi>Leeches</hi> ſhould ever be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</p>
            <p>Or in caſe thirſt doth not provoke them, they will drinke before they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e dry, drinke untill they become dry, ſo that thirſt overtakes drunkenneſſe, as <hi>fooles</hi> runne into the <hi>River</hi> to avoid a ſhower of <hi>raine.</hi> Yea while they are in the drinking Schoole, they are bound by their ſaw of good fellowſhip, (and would be ſo, were there no ſuch law) to be pouring in at their <hi>mouths,</hi> or whiffing out at their <hi>noſes;</hi> one ſerving as a ſhooing-horne to the other: for <hi>Tobacco</hi> being <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>dry,</hi> muſt have a qualifier of <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>moiſt</hi> from the <hi>pot;</hi> and that againe being <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>moiſt,</hi> muſt have a qualifier of <hi>hot</hi> and <hi>dry,</hi> from the <hi>pipe:</hi> which makes them like <hi>Rats</hi> baned <hi>Rats, drinke</hi> and vent, <hi>vent</hi> and drinke; <hi>Sellingers round</hi> and the ſame againe. Beſides they drinke one liquor to draw on another; not to quench, but to increaſe thirſt; not to qualifie, but to inkindle heat. In which their ſwiniſh ſwilling, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble ſo many frogs in a <hi>puddle,</hi> or <hi>water ſnakes</hi> in a <hi>pond:</hi> for their whole exerciſe, yea religion, is to drinke; they even drowne themſelves on the dry land. As O the deluges of wine, and ſtrong drinke, that one true Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard devoures, and cauſeth to be devoured! who never drinkes but double, for he muſt be pledged. Yea, if there be ten in company, every one muſt drinke as much as he; and he will drinke untill his eyes ſtare like two <hi>bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Stars,</hi> ſo that they drinke more ſpirits in a night, then their fleſh and braines be worth.</p>
            <p>But in the meane time; how many thouſands which are hard driven with poverty, or the exigents of warre, might be relieved, with that which theſe men ſpend like beaſts? while that is throwne out of one <hi>Swines noſe,</hi> and <hi>mouth,</hi> and <hi>guts,</hi> which would refreſh a whole family? And doth not the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry eccho of this ſinne, this exceſſive devouring the good creatures of God, together with the teares of the poore; dayly cry in his eares for vengeance on all that uſe it? if not for a famine upon the whole land for their ſakes,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151474:10"/>(who turne the Sanctuary of life, into the ſhambles of death,) and becauſe they are ſuffered? Yes undoubtedly. Yea O Lord, it is thy unſpeakable mercy, that our Land (which hath beene ſo long ſicke of this drunken diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and ſo long ſurfetted of this ſinne) doth not ſpue us all out, which are the inhabitants.</p>
            <p>§ 8. Now by that theſe <hi>gut mongers</hi> have doubled their mornings draught, or <hi>gulped</hi> downe ſo many quarts, as they can well overcome, <hi>(for I will tye my ſelfe, to the Drunkards method)</hi> their hearts come up as eaſily as ſome of their drinke. For wine, ſaith <hi>Plato,</hi> is the daughter of verity; the glaſſe of the minde, ſaith <hi>Euripides:</hi> Yea let him get but a cup or two more in his pate, his limitleſſe tongue ſhall clatter like a <hi>window</hi> looſe in the <hi>winde;</hi> and you may aſſoone perſwade a <hi>ſtone</hi> to ſpeake, as him to be ſilent. For then it fares with his <hi>clapper,</hi> as with a ſicke mans <hi>pulſe;</hi> which alwayes beats, but ever out of order. Yea one Drunkard hath tongue enough for twenty men: it being like that <hi>clapper</hi> at <hi>Roane,</hi> which is ſo bigge, that it is ſaid to weigh without the <hi>Bell,</hi> more then ſixe hundred pounds. And what is their diſcourſe?</p>
            <p>Firſt, they diſcover all <hi>ſecrets;</hi> for like as when the <hi>wine purgeth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch,</hi> that which is in the <hi>bottome</hi> cometh up to the <hi>brim,</hi> and ſwimmeth aloft; or elſe it breaketh the <hi>veſſell,</hi> and runneth all abroad: Even ſo drunkenneſſe diſcovers the ſecrets of the heart. And indeed, if diſcretion, and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be as <hi>hoopes</hi> to a <hi>veſſell;</hi> how ſhould theſe <hi>hogſheads</hi> keepe their <hi>liquor,</hi> if ye take away thoſe hoopes? It is the property of a drunkard to diſgorge his boſome with his ſtomach, to empty his minde with his maw: he can ill rule his hands, but worſe his tongue; fat cups oyle that ſo, that it cannot ſticke, and makes it ſo laskative, that it cannot hold. And whatſoever is in the <hi>heart</hi> of a ſober man, is found in the <hi>tongue</hi> of a Drunkard. Drinke diſapparels the ſoule, and is the betrayer of the minde: it turnes the <hi>key</hi> of the tongue, and makes it <hi>unlock</hi> that counſell, which before wiſdome had in keeping. And experience ſhewes, that when a man is drunke, you may thruſt your hand into him like an <hi>Eele skinne,</hi> and ſtrip his inſide out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</p>
            <p>Or ſuppoſe you urge him not, the wine having ſet his tongue at liberty, it ſhall reſemble <hi>Bacchus his Liber pater,</hi> and goe like the <hi>ſayle of a Windmill:</hi> for as a great <hi>gale of winde</hi> whirleth the ſayles about; ſo aboundance of wine whirleth his tongue about, and keeps it in perpetuall motion. For now he <hi>rayles,</hi> now he <hi>ſcoffes,</hi> now he <hi>lyes,</hi> now he <hi>ſlanders,</hi> now he <hi>ſeduces,</hi> talkes <hi>bawdy, ſweares, bannes, foames;</hi> and cannot be quiet untill his tongue be wormed. Nor is he more <hi>lewd</hi> then <hi>lowd;</hi> for commonly a lewd tongue is a lowd one; and a lowd tongue a lewd one. Impudent ſpeakers are like <hi>gaping oyſters;</hi> which being opened either ſtinke, or there is nothing in them.</p>
            <p>§ 9. But to keepe cloſe to Drunkards, this <hi>Cacodemons</hi> diſcourſe is all <hi>quarrelling, ſcoffing,</hi> or <hi>ſcurrilous:</hi> for as he hath a <hi>ſpightfull</hi> tongue in his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, ſo he hath a <hi>beaſtly</hi> tongue in his <hi>mirth;</hi> as theſe two inſeparably attend each other.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151474:11"/>
            <p>Firſt, a ſpightfull tongue in his anger; for if you mark him then, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving more <hi>rage</hi> then <hi>reaſon;</hi> he enterlaceth all his diſcourſe, either with reviling the <hi>preſent,</hi> or backbiting the <hi>abſent.</hi> Now all his prayers are curſes, and all his relations lyes: as talkative, and lying, are two birds which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes flye out of one neſt. To be ſhort, heare him when he is in this veine, and but ſeriouſly conſider his condition, you would think, that by a juſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>God</hi> he were metamorphoſed, like <hi>Hecuba</hi> the wife of <hi>Priamus,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>dog;</hi> for without queſtion their <hi>wits</hi> are <hi>ſhorter,</hi> and their <hi>tongues longer</hi> then to demonſtrate them rationall creatures.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Drunkards communication is ever filthy, and beaſtly, full of all ribaldry, and baudineſſe: no filthy talke, or rotten ſpeech whatſoever, comes amiſſe to a Drunkard. Yea no word ſavours well with them, that is not unſavoury: their onely muſicke (and ſo it fares with all the rude rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) is ribaldry; modeſty, and ſober merriment with them is dulneſſe. So that from the beginning to the end, he belcheth forth nothing, but what is as farre from <hi>truth, piety, reaſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, modeſty;</hi> as that the <hi>moone</hi> came down from Heaven, to viſit <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O the beaſtlineſſe which burnes in their unchaſt, and <hi>impure mindes!</hi> that ſmoakes out of their <hi>polluted mouthes!</hi> a man would thinke that even the Devill himſelfe ſhould bluſh, to heare his childe ſo talke; as how doth his mouth run over with falſhoods, againſt both <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and <hi>Preachers?</hi> what ſpeaks he leſſe then <hi>Whoredomes, Adulteries, inceſts</hi> at every word? Yea, heare two or three of them talke, you will change the <hi>Lycaomans</hi> language, and ſay, Devils are come up in the likeneſſe of men.</p>
            <p>And becauſe it is a ſmall matter with them, to meddle with their equalls, or to ſit upon their pariſh Prieſt, (as thoſe <hi>Hogſheads</hi> terme him) in ſuch mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings they will viſit a whole <hi>Droceſſe,</hi> and <hi>Province;</hi> nay, the ſageſt <hi>Judge</hi> and graveſt <hi>Counſellor,</hi> and greateſt <hi>Peere</hi> in the land; muſt do ſervice to their <hi>Court,</hi> and be ſummoned before the <hi>Alebench:</hi> according to that in the <hi>Pſalmes, They ſet their mouths againſt Heaven, and their tongues walke through the earth, Pſal.</hi> 73.9. And having huft their ſmoake into the face of theſe, they will have a health to King <hi>Charles;</hi> and what not, for the honour of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 10. Thirdly, from <hi>wicked talking,</hi> hee proceeds to curſed, and <hi>impious ſwearing, blaſpheming, &amp;c.</hi> as you ſhall rarely ſee a Drunkard, but hee is a great ſwearer: and not of petty oathes, but thoſe proditious, and fearfull ones, of wounds and bloud; the damned language of <hi>Ruffins,</hi> and <hi>Monſters of the earth:</hi> together with <hi>God danne me,</hi> which words many of them uſe ſuperficially, if they repent not. Yea they ſweare and curſe, as if Heaven were deafe to their noiſe. <hi>O the numberleſſe number of oaths and blaſphemies, that one blacke-mouthed Drunkard</hi> ſpits out in defiance as it were of <hi>God,</hi> and all prohibitions to the contrary! I dare affirme it, had ſome one of them <hi>three thouſand pounds per annum,</hi> his means would ſcarce hold out, to pay thoſe ſmall twelve peny mulcts, which our <hi>Stat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te Law</hi> impoſes upon ſwearers, were it duly executed; and if ſo, to what number will the oaths and curſes amount, which are ſworne, and uttered through the whole <hi>Land?</hi> Yea in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151474:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſome one <hi>Alehouſe,</hi> or <hi>Taverne;</hi> where they fit all day in Troopes, doing that in earneſt, which we have ſeen boyes do in ſport; ſtand on their heads and ſhake their heeles againſt <hi>Heaven.</hi> Where even to heare, how the name of the <hi>Lord Jeſus</hi> is pierced, and <hi>Gods name</hi> blaſphemed, would make a <hi>dumbe</hi> man <hi>ſpeake,</hi> a <hi>dead</hi> man almoſt to <hi>quake:</hi> in which they reſemble a mad <hi>dog</hi> that flyeth in his Maſters face that keepes him. But how they ſweare away their ſalvation, curſe away their bleſſing: I have ſhewen at <hi>large,</hi> in <hi>another Tract.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 11. Now after the pots for a while have ſtopt all their mouthes, (though every man had his ſhare before) and they forgot what was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpoken; You ſhall have one for very pure love, and want of other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, weepe in his fellowes boſome: another ſit kiſſing of his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, not without ſome ſhort ſentence, nothing to the purpoſe. A third ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his mouth on the racke with laughter, (wiſe were the man that could tell at what.) A fourth ſwaggering, and ſwearing, becauſe the wine was brought him no ſooner. A fift (for I paſſe him that ſits there in a corner nodding, and ſlavouring) fals downe uppon his marrow bones, in devotion to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and up with the pot hand-ſmooth. After which every one that is awake ſings his ſong, ſeaſoning the ſame with many a goodly belch: their one in ſtead of a <hi>Harpe,</hi> takes a <hi>knife</hi> and a <hi>quart pot;</hi> with which hee will make fine muſicke. Another in his ſong commends his <hi>miſtris;</hi> another the goodneſſe of the wine; another being better skilled in <hi>proſe</hi> then <hi>meeter,</hi> relates all the paſſages between him and his <hi>wife</hi> at home. Where to heare how they all lay their heads together; plot and conſult how to charme and tame their poore wives: would make a diſcreet <hi>Maid</hi> reſolve never to marry ſo long as ſhee is able to worke with a knitting needle. Another tels how many quarts, he and ſo many more dranke at ſuch a meeting; another be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnes to argue of <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>matters of State;</hi> another (for wine de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending, cauſeth words ſtill to aſcend) bragges of his lying with ſuch a woman, into whoſe company he could never yet be admitted; another again boaſts how he jeered ſuch a <hi>Roundhead</hi> or <hi>Puritane:</hi> (for ſo are all abſtemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men, in the <hi>Epicures words,</hi> or a <hi>beaſts language</hi>) and the drinke having bitten him, he runnes up and downe like a <hi>mad dog,</hi> ſnapping at every body; and many a good man may ſay with <hi>David, I became a ſong of the drunkards.</hi> Another quarrels with his friend, that after the <hi>third health</hi> refuſeth to drinke any more: and being at length delivered of their company, they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute the caſe about his departure; and are ſo vext, that they gnaw their owne tongues for ſpight; and call him the baſeſt names their <hi>block-heads</hi> can thinke of; every one ſtoutly affirming, that he can be no <hi>honeſt man</hi> who refuſeth to <hi>pledge</hi> them. For as the utmoſt of a <hi>Drunkards honeſty is good fellowſhip,</hi> ſo it is an unpardonable crime, not to drinke equall with the reſt, or to depart while they are able to ſpeake ſenſe. Whence many have loſt their lives, becauſe they would not drink. Another ſals a rhyming all in Satyre againſt the reſt that are abſent; and perhaps ſteepes his jeſt in his own laughter; which being liked, and laughed at, they all fall a rhyming;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151474:12"/>then every one in his order muſt play the Poet out of the inſpiration of <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> only; for <hi>Sibylla</hi> like, they never yeeld any <hi>Oracle,</hi> except they are firſt poſſeſt with a <hi>fury:</hi> and the <hi>Muſes</hi> may go hang for any roome they have here.</p>
            <p>Their <hi>Library</hi> is a large roome, ranked full of <hi>Pots, Cannes, Glaſſes, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco pipes, raſhers</hi> on the coales, <hi>red herrings, a gammon of Bacon, Caveare, Anchovis,</hi> or ſuch like ſhooing-hornes to whet on their appetites, (I meane to more drinke; for that they are no <hi>Trencher men,</hi> is all their boaſt, and all they have to be proud of,) together with a <hi>Jordane</hi> for their urine on the one ſide, and a <hi>boule</hi> for their vomit on the other. For they will vomit, as if they were ſo many live <hi>Whales</hi> ſpuing up the <hi>Ocean:</hi> which done, they can drinke againe afreſh.</p>
            <p>§ 12. Now although the wiſeſt of them cannot make two true verſes in his mother tongue, in three houres: yea although they be the verieſt <hi>lack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latins,</hi> and the moſt <hi>unalphabetical raggabaſha's</hi> that ever lived: yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding (for ſtand well they cannot) they will one with a <hi>coale,</hi> another with a <hi>candle,</hi> fill all the <hi>wals</hi> and <hi>ſeelings</hi> with <hi>Epithalamiums, Elegies,</hi> and <hi>Epitaphs;</hi> which done are expounded to the reſt of the company, if any be <hi>awake</hi> to heare them. Your eares would <hi>bliſter</hi> to read them; though it would do a <hi>deafe</hi> mans heart good to <hi>heare</hi> them, or a <hi>blinde</hi> mans to <hi>ſee</hi> them.</p>
            <p>And yet poore ſoules they thinke themſelves wiſer then <hi>Solomon;</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bribed with ſelfe conceit, what cannot they <hi>do,</hi> what do they not <hi>know,</hi> what will they not <hi>ſay?</hi> Whence it is their ſpeech is much though little to the purpoſe: and what ever the queſtion be, the truth is on their ſide: all is ſpoken in <hi>print</hi> that is ſpoken by them, though their phraſe (the apparell of their ſpeech) hath a <hi>raſh outſide, and fuſtian linings.</hi> Yea all the Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards <hi>Geeſe</hi> are <hi>Swans;</hi> and all their vertues <hi>ten foot long.</hi> As for faults they have none; for poore ſoules they ſee neither their <hi>ſlips,</hi> nor <hi>wants.</hi> In a word, they hold all the world <hi>Dunces,</hi> beſides themſelves and will ſweare they are but <hi>ſhallow fellowes,</hi> that do not drinke <hi>ſacke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas, if they can but <hi>breake a jeſt</hi> (as many of them are like <hi>Sarmantius</hi> a gentleman of <hi>Rome;</hi> who was famous only for his <hi>ſcoffing;</hi>) then they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit of themſelves as <hi>Menecrates</hi> did, who (although not worthy to be <hi>Aeſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapius</hi> his <hi>Apothecaries boy</hi>) would needs be <hi>Jupiter;</hi> and to ſpeake rightly, the <hi>beane</hi> of all their honour, lyes in <hi>ſcoffes,</hi> and <hi>jeeres;</hi> for take from theſe <hi>Aſpes</hi> but their <hi>poyſon</hi> and <hi>ſting,</hi> you utterly undo them; they have nothing left of any uſe. All their worth lyes in <hi>wit-crackers,</hi> as ſome in the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> have their wealth in <hi>ſquibs,</hi> and <hi>fire-workes,</hi> though it were happy for them, if they wanted this wit too; and <hi>Satan</hi> ſhould do them a greater plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, if he did not ſo <hi>prompt</hi> them in ſcoffes: for like <hi>Abſaloms</hi> haire, it proves but an ornament to hang themſelves with all; and the beſt office their wit does them, is either to <hi>ſpit out friends</hi> with their tongues, or <hi>laugh them into enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 13. But are they ſo wiſe, becauſe they thinke themſelves ſo? No, no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151474:12"/>more then <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was great, becauſe he called himſelfe a great man. For what ever they thinke, by the rule of <hi>ſcripture</hi> every Drunkard is a foole, <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.6. And experience ſhewes, that the greateſt <hi>bowzars</hi> are the greateſt <hi>buzzards</hi> in the world: that they have moſt <hi>leaden conceits, dull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, droſſy wits, groſſe and muddy affections. A fooles voice</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>) <hi>is knowne by a multitude of words, Eccleſiaſtes</hi> 10.14. and babling drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards can better afford you a <hi>Sea</hi> of words, then a <hi>drop</hi> of wit. As marke whether their diſcourſe be not more <hi>ſound</hi> then <hi>ſubſtance; winde</hi> then <hi>matter;</hi> as ever where is leaſt <hi>braine,</hi> there is moſt <hi>tongue,</hi> and lowdeſt, ſaith <hi>Socrates:</hi> even as a <hi>Bruers Cart</hi> upon the <hi>ſtones,</hi> makes <hi>moſt noiſe,</hi> when his <hi>veſſels</hi> are <hi>emptieſt;</hi> the full <hi>veſſell</hi> gives you a <hi>ſoft anſwer,</hi> but <hi>ſound liquor:</hi> ſo a knowing, and ſolid man will either be ſilent, or his words ſhall be better then ſilence; whereas they that ſpeake much, ſeldome ſpeake well. I might proceed to his knowledge in the beſt things; and ſhew you that whereas ſome are like the <hi>Moone</hi> at full, have all their light towards <hi>Earth,</hi> none to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Heaven:</hi> others like the <hi>Moone</hi> at wane, or change; have all their light to <hi>Heaven wards,</hi> none to the <hi>Earth:</hi> Drunkards are like the <hi>Moone</hi> in Eclipſe, as having no light in it ſelfe; neither towards Earth, nor towards Heaven. Though they are apt to thinke themſelves <hi>Giants for wit,</hi> and <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles for light</hi> and judgement even in divinity alſo: which makes them ſo put themſelves forward: as how oft have I ſeen a Caſe of <hi>Leather</hi> ſtuft with winde, (as he in <hi>Marcellus Donatus</hi> thought himſelfe) A very beefe brained fellow, that hath had only impudence enough to ſhew himſelfe a foole; thruſt into diſcourſes of Religion, thinking to get eſteeme; when all that he hath purchaſed thereby, hath been only the hiſſe of the wiſe, and a juſt deriſion from the abler judgements. Not unlike that <hi>German Clowne,</hi> who undertook to be very ready in the <hi>Ten Commandements;</hi> but being asked by the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> which was the firſt? he anſwered, <hi>Thou ſhalt not eat.</hi> If you doubt of it, do but aske the Drunkard <hi>a reaſon of his faith;</hi> and you ſhall ſee that hee can no more tell you, then the <hi>Winde</hi> can tell which laſt blow'd off my Hat.</p>
            <p>Yea the Drunkard is ſuch a foole, that he would be <hi>begged for a foole:</hi> I would faine know whether is wiſeſt, the <hi>prodigall waſter,</hi> or the <hi>covetous gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per?</hi> he that with a wanton <hi>eye,</hi> a licoriſh <hi>tongue,</hi> and a gameſome <hi>hand,</hi> indiſcreetly ravels out his <hi>Anceſtors</hi> faire <hi>poſſeſſions,</hi> it may bee an hundreth pounds <hi>per annum</hi> in three yeares: and then leads the reſt of his dayes in priſon, there to repent at leiſure; having for his attendants ſorrow, griefe, deriſion, beggery, contempt, &amp;c. Or he that to get an hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> and only poſſeſſe, not <hi>uſe</hi> the ſame after he hath got it, perhaps three yeares: is content to be weeping and wayling, and gnaſhing of teeth in the <hi>priſon of hell</hi> for evermore? without queſtion theſe two are both fools alike. But that Drunkards are none of the wiſeſt, I ſhall ſhew in the effects of <hi>drunkenneſſe:</hi> In the meane time I'le acquaint you with the <hi>cauſes,</hi> And</p>
            <p>§ 14. Firſt, one maine cauſe why their <hi>heaven</hi> is the <hi>Taverne,</hi> whence they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151474:13"/>never depart untill they have caſt up the <hi>reckoning:</hi> why like <hi>horſes</hi> they are onely guided by <hi>the mouth,</hi> is this; the pot is no ſooner from their lips, but they are <hi>melancholy;</hi> and their hearts as heavy, as if a <hi>milſtone</hi> lay upon it; reſembling the fly <hi>Pyrauſta,</hi> which dyes if out of the <hi>fire.</hi> I call it melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, becauſe they call it ſo; but the truth is, they are vexed like <hi>Saul</hi> with an evill ſpirit; which nothing will drive away but <hi>drinke,</hi> and <hi>tobacco;</hi> which is to them, as <hi>Davids</hi> Harp was to him, 1 Sam. 16.23.</p>
            <p>They ſo wound their conſciences with <hi>oathes,</hi> intentionall <hi>murthers, rapes,</hi> and other the like actuall uncleanneſſe; and ſo exceedingly provoke God; that they are even in this life rewarded with the <hi>ſtrapadoes</hi> of an hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſoul; <hi>wrackt in conſcience, and tortured with the very flaſhes of hel fire:</hi> which makes them many times to lay violent hands upon themſelves; being never well, nor in their <hi>owne place</hi> till they be in <hi>hell, Acts</hi> 1.25.</p>
            <p>When the horror of their <hi>oathes, blaſphemies, theſis, whoredomes,</hi> and other prodigious <hi>uncleanneſſe</hi> hath cauſed a dejection of ſpirit, and the <hi>worme of conſcience</hi> to ſting them; (as it fared with <hi>Cain,</hi> when he had murthered his brother <hi>Abel</hi>) how ſhould they remedy it? but (as if <hi>Satan</hi> alone could expell <hi>Satan</hi>) ſtraight to the Taverne, and drinke ſorrow, and care away. Or perhaps there is a <hi>factor for hel</hi> preſent, that cheares him up as <hi>Jezebel</hi> did <hi>Ahab;</hi> when he was ſicke for want of <hi>Naboths</hi> vineyard, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 21.7. crying, Come, you are melancholy; let us both to the <hi>Taverne,</hi> and <hi>Brothel-houſe;</hi> and ſo cures all his ſadneſſe for that time with a charme: wherein nevertheleſſe the principall ingredient is <hi>drinke;</hi> the common refuge of melancholy ſinners, their conſtant and never failing friend; to which alſo they are as conſtant: for when did the <hi>Sun</hi> ever ſee ſome of them ſober; and how are our <hi>Cities,</hi> and <hi>Townes peſtered,</hi> and our <hi>ſtreets ſtrewed</hi> with theſe filths? And this is the maine ground of all; for as they that have curſt and ſhrewiſh <hi>wives</hi> at home, love to ſtray abroad: ſo theſe men being moleſted with a ſcolding <hi>conſcience,</hi> are faine continually to <hi>drinke, play, riot,</hi> go to bed with their heads full of wine, and no ſooner awake but to it againe. So that their conſciences muſt knock at the doore a thouſand times, and they are never at home, or at leiſure to be ſpoke withall. Indeed at laſt they muſt be met, and found by this enemy, even as <hi>Ahab</hi> was by <hi>Eliah; ſtay</hi> they never ſo long, and <hi>ſtray</hi> they never ſo far, they muſt home at laſt, ſickneſſe will waken them, conſcience muſt ſpeake with them as a Maſter with his <hi>Trewant Scholar,</hi> after a long abſence; and then there are no men under Heaven, who more need that prayer <hi>Lord have mercy upon them.</hi> For a wicked mans peace will not alwayes laſt; at the end his guilt will gnaw him, with ſo much a ſharper tooth. Neither are they more <hi>jocund in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity,</hi> then in <hi>dyſaſters</hi> they are amazed.</p>
            <p>Whereas they ſhould eate, and drinke, and do all things to the glory of God; they drinke to this end only, that they may the eaſier forget <hi>God;</hi> forget him in his <hi>threats,</hi> which ſtick in their ſoules after ſome Sermon: forget him in his judgements, which have taken hold of ſome of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions; they drinke to the end they may drowne conſcience, and put off all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151474:13"/>thoughts of death and Hell; and to hearten and harden themſelves againſt all the meſſages of <hi>God,</hi> and threats of thr Law. Whereas if they had wit, and were not paſt grace; they would both invite, and welcome this <hi>Angell</hi> or Meſſenger of the Lord, ſo ſoone as the waters be troubled. But many a time is poore <hi>Chriſt</hi> (offering to be new borne in thee) thruſt into the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, while lewd companions, by their drinking, muſick, and jeſts take up all the beſt roomes in the Inne of thine heart; which yet are but <hi>miſerable comforters, Phyſitians of no value:</hi> Yea let ten conſorts of muſick be added, all ſhall not drowne the clamorous cries of conſcience: nor can the whole world afford an expurgation of this melancholy. Yea I'le appeal from your ſelves in drink, to your ſelves in your ſober fits; whether it fares not with you, as it did with <hi>Menippus;</hi> who went downe into Hell to ſeeke content; for what is this other in mitigating the pangs of conſcience, then as a ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of gold to a gauled horſe? or a draught of poiſon to quench a mans thirſt?</p>
            <p>Alas, they which ſtrive to cure their preſent miſery (in this caſe) with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent mirth; have not their miſery ſo much taken away, as changed; and of temporall made eternall. <hi>Thou haſt taken thy pleaſure</hi> (ſaith <hi>Abraham</hi> to that belly-god frying in Hell flames) <hi>therefore art thou now tormented, Luke</hi> 16.25. Little do drunkards conſider, that the Devill is a fiſher, ſinne his hooke, pleaſure his bait, fooles his fiſh; or the danger they are in, even making a recreation of miſery, ſporting themſelves in their ſins, round about the pits brinke without fear: when as they are every houre ready to tople into hel, that bottomleſs gulfe of eaſeleſs, and everlaſting flames. <hi>They ſpend their dayes in mirth,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job, and ſuddenly they goe downe into hell, Iob</hi> 21.13.</p>
            <p>Indeed, your charmes may with their pleaſantneſs, bring conſcience into ſome ſhort ſlumbers: but it waketh eftſoons, and in ſpight of all your ſpells rageth as before. Yea, if but ſickneſs come, theſe carnall delights will runne from you afrighted, like Rats from an houſe on fire. Pleaſure like <hi>Orpah,</hi> kiſſes, but parts: onely griefe like <hi>Ruth,</hi> weeps and tarryes with you. No joy will downe, till there be hope of a pardon, as it fares with condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned perſons.</p>
            <p>So that no hand can heale you, but the very ſame which wounded you; the wounds of the minde can onely be cured by the word of God: which teacheth what is to be ſaid, what to be knowne, what to be beleeved, what to be avoided, and what not.</p>
            <p>Thus in ſtead of repenting, and labouring in a lawfull calling: which (ſaith <hi>Fulgentius</hi>) is the onely cure of <hi>melancholy,</hi> and deſtruction of all vices: they adde ſinne to ſinne, leaving Gods remedies, to ſeeke remedy of the Devill; whoſe office is not to quench fire, but to kindle it; even the fire of luſt, with the fire of drunkenneſs here; and with thoſe two, the fire of hell hereafter. But</p>
            <p>§ 15. Secondly, to this may be added the Drunkards <hi>idleneſſe</hi> as another cauſe; yea, idleneſs is the cauſe both of drunkenneſs, melancholy, and all the reſidue of evils which accompany the ſame. For as idleneſſe is the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151474:14"/>only opportunity: ſo it is the moſt corrupting flye that can blow in any humane mind: we learne to do ill, by doing what is next it, nothing: an idle perſon is good for nothing, but to propagate ſinne; as ground unoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied produces nothing but noiſome, and unprofitable things. The ſoule is like a <hi>River,</hi> that is alwayes in progreſſion: the heart like a <hi>Wherry,</hi> either goes forward or backward. If the minde be not buſied with good thoughts, it will fill with evill cogitations: the death of the one, is but the birth of the other.</p>
            <p>Now drunkards generally, either do nothing, or that which is worſe then nothing; all the drunkards labour, is to ſatisfie his luſts, and all his life nought elſe but a viciſſitude of devouring, and venting: as how many of them make it their whole trade and imployment to keep company, to go from their beds to the Taphouſe, (for the drunkard thinks no wine good, that is brought over two threſholds) from the <hi>Tap-houſe</hi> to the <hi>Play-houſe,</hi> where they make a match for the <hi>Brothel-houſe,</hi> and from thence backe to the <hi>Taverne,</hi> and ſo to bed againe. Or elſe they ſpend the whole day, yea, every day in <hi>howſing,</hi> and <hi>bowling,</hi> and taking <hi>Tobacco:</hi> for they onely ſit to <hi>eat,</hi> and <hi>drinke,</hi> lye downe to <hi>ſleep,</hi> and riſe up to <hi>play:</hi> this is all their exerciſe, herein lyes all their worth; and no marvaile, for if the world be a mans God, pleaſure muſt needs be his Religion. The company-keeper is the barreneſt piece of earth in all the <hi>Orbe:</hi> the Common-wealth hath no more uſe of him, then <hi>Jerchoam</hi> had of his withered hand. He is like the dumbe <hi>Jacke</hi> in a <hi>Virginall;</hi> for he hath not ſo much as a voice in the common-wealth.</p>
            <p>What is recorded of <hi>Margites,</hi> namely that he never plowed nor digged, nor did any thing all his life long, that might tend to any good: is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly verified in him, he is not more nimble tongued, then laſie handed, as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> confeſt of himſelfe. Drunkards are like ſo many <hi>Gnats,</hi> for as Gnats do nothing but play up and downe in the warme <hi>Sunne</hi> and ſing; and when they have done ſit downe and ſting the next hand or face they can ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: ſo drunkards miſerably ſpend their good houres in wicked, or unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable paſtime; ſit downe and backbite their neighbours. And ſo much of the ſecond cauſe.</p>
            <p>§ 16. Thirdly, ſottiſh <hi>feare,</hi> and baſe <hi>cowardlineſſe</hi> is another maine cauſe; men dare not forſooth, refuſe to go to the Taverne, when the motion is made, (and they ſeldome meet one another, but they make the motion) nor refuſe when they come there, to do as the reſt; that is, to drinke drunke, be it to the wounding of <hi>conſcience,</hi> hazard of <hi>health, life, ſoule, &amp;c.</hi> for feare of ſeeming ſingular. Yea he ſhall be ſcofft at, and called Round-head, or Puritane, if he will not revell it with them in a ſhoarleſſe exceſſe, and the coward had rather goe to hell, then be ſo reputed; ſo that not God, not their conſciences come into any regard with them; but they ſhall bee mocked, the caſe of <hi>Zedekiah, Ier.</hi> 38.19. of <hi>Saul,</hi> who ſtood more upon the praiſe of men, then the favour of God, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.30. and of <hi>Herod,</hi> when he cut off <hi>Iohn Baptiſts</hi> head; for he did it full ſore againſt his will, and onely to anſwer the expectation of the ſtanders by, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.8, 9. Whence
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151474:14"/>we may gather, that too much modeſty, and want of courage to deny the requeſts of a ſeeming friend, hath loſt millions of ſoules; that this is one notable meanes to fill hell, loathneſs to diſpleaſe. And certainely there is ſomething in it, that the <hi>fearefull</hi> are placed by the holy Ghoſt, in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front of that damned crue; who ſhall <hi>have their part in the lake which burneth with fire and brimſtone, Rev.</hi> 21.8. they are aſhamed <hi>of Chriſt,</hi> and of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs before men on earth; therefore <hi>Chriſt will be aſhamed of them, and not owne them before his Father, and his holy Angels in heaven.</hi> And indeed it is a damnable plauſibility, ſo to regard the vaine approbation, or cenſure of the beholders: as in the meane time to neglect the allowance or judgement of <hi>God.</hi> A good heart will rather fall out with all the world, then with his maker, then with his conſcience. Nor is hee more wicked then fooliſh, that will gaine the worlds favour, and loſe Gods; eſcape deriſion, to meet with confuſion.</p>
            <p>§ 17. Againe, other reaſons and cauſes there bee of it (though indeed there is no reaſon in it) which I muſt be forced to paſſe over with onely na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming them, as firſt, <hi>pride,</hi> or <hi>reputation of good fellowſhip</hi> is one ſpeciall <hi>cauſe; covetouſneſſe another; evill company a third, &amp;c.</hi> for they will by no meanes grant, that they drinke for the love of drinke. No, will theſe ſwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bowles ſay, yea ſweare that is the baſeſt thing in the world, they are Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cures indeed that will do ſo; though they love it (as they ſhould do God) above all, above <hi>health, wealth, credit, child, wife, life, heaven, ſalvation,</hi> all: calling for it, as the Pope once for his diſh; even in deſpight of heaven. For is not their gullet, their God? do they not ſacrifice more to their God <hi>Belly,</hi> then thoſe <hi>Babylonians</hi> did to their God <hi>Bel?</hi> Alas, they no more care for wine, then <hi>Eſau</hi> did for his pottage, for which he <hi>ſold his birthright:</hi> then <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> did, who made away a whole Kingdome for drinke: then <hi>Philoxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and <hi>Melanthius</hi> did, who, that the drinke might yeeld them the more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in going downe to their ſtomachs, wiſh't the one a Swans throat, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a Cranes neck. For let them ſay or ſweare what they will, i'le beleeve the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> who makes us privy to their heart and thoughts, <hi>Eſay</hi> 56.12. where they confeſſe as much; and that other ſcripture 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.16. &amp; 2.12. where Drunkards are called the ſonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> that is, all belly, and for the belly.</p>
            <p>Yea let ſome good fellow or other tell me, whether it would not make his teeth water, and his guts grumble; yea whether in envy he would not feed upon his owne heart to ſee his companions drinke their healths round, while he ſate by only to ſee and heare them? And if ſo, confeſſe that you drink not to pleaſe others, but your ſelves; (as <hi>Canus</hi> played upon his harp) not for your friends ſake, but for the drinkes ſake; that you drinke not out of need, but luſt; not for health, but for delight.</p>
            <p>§ 18. But to goe on, (for I may ſeeme to have left them) what hath been ſpoken proves them much worſe then beaſts: but this is a ſmall evill with them; this is but to worke out their owne damnations: their chiefe care, induſtry, and delight is to infect others: the ſerpents ſpeciall venome,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151474:15"/>wherewith theſe his elves be intoxicated, is, to make others more beaſts then themſelves. Yea Drunkards being the Devils deputies, to turn others into beaſts, will make themſelves Devils. Wherein they have a notable dexteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, making the Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>houſe, or Taverne, their ſtudy; their <hi>circle</hi> the Pot, themſelves the <hi>conjurers,</hi> mens ſoules the <hi>hire,</hi> reputation of good fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>charme,</hi> the <hi>characters</hi> healths, the <hi>Goblin raiſed,</hi> is the ſpirit of the buttery; and to drinke God out of their <hi>bearts,</hi> health out of their <hi>bodies,</hi> wit out of their <hi>heads,</hi> ſtrength out of their <hi>joints,</hi> all the money out of their <hi>purſes,</hi> all the drinke out of the <hi>Brewers barrels, wife</hi> and <hi>children</hi> out of doors, the <hi>land</hi> out of quiet, <hi>plenty</hi> out of the Kingdome, is all their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe Agents for the Devill, Drunkards, practice nothing but the art of d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bauching men; for they will take no paines, unleſſe the Devill ſets them on worke: but being ſet like <hi>beaſts</hi> to draw in the Devils <hi>Teeme;</hi> they <hi>will l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad captive unſtable ſoules to ſin, with cords of vanity, as it were with a Cart rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Eſay</hi> 5.18. For to ſinne, theſe pernicious ſeducers, Devils in the ſhape of men, are no niggards of their paines. As ô how much is hell beholding to them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> would take great paines, <hi>compaſſe Sea and Land, to make one the childe of Hell,</hi> like <hi>themſelves:</hi> ſo what will not ſome Drunkards do, or ſpend; to make a ſober man a Drunkard, or to drink another drunkard under the table?</p>
            <p>§ 19. Now for the effecting of this, what comparable to drinking of Lealths? which <hi>Antiſthenes</hi> cals the onely occaſion, and meanes of ſurfeiting, and diſorder. Another very fitly, the palley or ſhooing-horne to all drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe and exceſs. For their drinking and beginning of healths is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely, and ſerves to no other end, but to draw men on to drinke more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, then elſe they would or ſhould do.</p>
            <p>As le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a ſober, and religious man fall into their company; as a purſe of mony may fall into a ſtinking privy: O how they will conſpire to provoke his unwilling appetite, with drunken healths! and if they can (like the <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>iſh harlot</hi>) make him taſte poiſon in a golden cup: O then they will ſing, and rejoice as in the diviſion of a ſpoile! and brag that they have drenched ſobriety, and blinded the light, and ever after be a ſnuſſing of this Taper, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13.4. and the like to every one they light upon, which is a moſt wofull glory: yea, how will they winde men in, by drinking firſt a health to ſuch a man, then to ſuch a woman my miſtris, then to every ones miſtris, then to ſuch a great perſon; naming ſome <hi>Lord</hi> or <hi>Lady,</hi> or near <hi>friend;</hi> their <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> their <hi>Captaines, Commanders, Parents, Kindreds,</hi> or <hi>Companions</hi> health; and that not ſeldome upon their knees: ſo making <hi>Gods</hi> of others, <hi>Beaſts</hi> of themſelves. Or rather doing homage to Satan, for health-drinking upon their knees was firſt invented, and uſed as the Devils drinke-offering; or as a part of that honour, and adoration which the Pagan <hi>Idolaters, ſorcerers,</hi> and <hi>witches,</hi> conſecrated, and gave to <hi>Beelzeb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b</hi> the Prince of Devils, and thoſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Devill-gods</hi> which they uſed to worſhip: as <hi>Baſil</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> affirme: ſo that it's moſt rancke, and devilliſh Idolatry.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151474:15"/>
            <p>And laſt of all, they will drinke the <hi>Kings</hi> or the <hi>Queenes</hi> health: as taking it for granted, that none dare refuſe to pledge their healths, be they willing or unwilling, able or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mable; and by this meanes they will winde men in to drinke, even till their <hi>braines,</hi> their <hi>wits,</hi> their <hi>tongues,</hi> their <hi>eyes,</hi> their <hi>feet,</hi> their <hi>ſenſes,</hi> and all their <hi>members</hi> faile them. For commonly when theſe friends fall a drinking of healths; it is as enemies fall to fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with weapons, to ſhew their valour, and to get the maſtery; for hee is of moſt reputation with them, that is able to drinke moſt; and hee gets the greateſt honour, that can drinke the reſt off their legs. Yea, if they but meet with a man that can gulpe downe wine through the channell of his throat without interſpiration betweene gulpes, (as the <hi>Crocodile</hi> cats, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out moving of her nether jaw) they thinke he deſerves ſome great preferment. As <hi>Tiberius</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> preferred many to honors in his time, becauſe they were famous whoremaſters, and ſturdy drinkers. Yea if they might have their wils, none ſhould refuſe to be drunke unpuniſhed; or be drunke un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded at the common charge. Yea, they not onely thinke exceſſive drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worthy all honour during life; but they looke their aſſociates ſhould not ceaſe to honour them being dead; by mentioning their rare exploits herein.</p>
            <p>§ 20. But O you ſottiſh ſenſualiſts! how hath the Devill bewitched you, to magnifie, honour, and applaud all that are enthralled to this worſe then ſwiniſh ſwilling? and on the otherſide, to viliſie, rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oach and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>value, all that hate and loath it in their judgements; or elſe renownce it in their practice? Is it poſſible that the reaſonable ſoule of man (not profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly barbarous) ſhould be capable of ſuch a monſter? certainly if I had not known the truth and probate of it by ocular and experimental demonſtration from day to day; I could hardly bring my underſtanding to believe, that men, that <hi>Chriſtians</hi> ſhould be of ſuch a reprobate judgement, as to affect, admire, adore &amp;c. ſo <hi>foule,</hi> ſo <hi>baſe,</hi> ſo <hi>beaſtly,</hi> ſo <hi>unamiable,</hi> ſo <hi>unfruitfull, unprofi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>able, unpleaſant, unnaturall</hi> a vice as this is in moſt mens judgements, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Nay I cannot beleeve what I have both ſeene, and lieard in this caſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for it is not poſſible for the moſt corrupted heart, to thinke that any ſhould be honoured for villany, and for honeſty to be contemned. But rather that every drunkard in his more ſerious cogitations, thinkes of his fellow dying in this ſinne without repentance, a fit Saint to be canonized for the Devill. For not ſeldome are wicked mens judgements forced to yeeld unto that truth, againſt which their affections maintaine a rebellion.</p>
            <p>But it is admirable to thinke, and incredible to beleeve, how the Devill blindes them in this particular; which makes them that they care not what they ſpend, nor how much they drinke for popular applauſe, and to have o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers commend them for joviall; to be reputed generous, and brave blades. For opinion is all they ſtand upon, and that from men more gallant then wiſe, that have more heart then braine; yea more luſt, pride, and ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance then either. The ſame and reputation of good fellowſhip with them; is more ſweet then life, then ſalvation; for they had rather go to hell, then
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151474:16"/>be counted Puritanes for ſhaking hands with their drunken aſſociates. So p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oud are they of baſeneſſe, yea of ſhame; for let one commend the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard for a notable good fellow; another more wiſe, will reply, the better the worſe.</p>
            <p>And no leſſe ſottiſh is their opinion of victory: when even in conquering they are moſt overcome; for whileſt they triumph in a drunken victory, or conqueſt over their friends; Satan gets the victory over them. In exceſſive drinking they have overcome all their companions: this they ſee and boaſt of; but they ſee not how they are overcome, ſhamefully foiled, and utterly overthrowne by the Devill their chiefe enemy; under whoſe laſh they are like to be everlaſtingly.</p>
            <p>Beſides, what office ſo baſe? the hangmans is bad enough; but to be a Tempter, todeſtroy ſouls, to weare the livery of Satan, to be a penſioner of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el, at the command of that malignant and degenerous ſpirit, this is the moſt ignominious, and diſhonourable name and ſhame, that can be. To be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>angmans ſervant is an honour to it: for to ſeduce, and draw others to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, is the onely proper part of a Fiend or Devill.</p>
            <p>§ 21. I grant the Devill ſo blindes, and bewitches them, that they think the reputation of good fellowſhip the onely name, and fame, and themſelves the onely men alive; brave, generous, free, and bountifull blades: and all others but baſe, and covetous hoggrubbers. But all that are wiſe, or ſober winded, account them the very ſcum of the nation; and good for nought but to ſtand in the midſt of a breach, when the <hi>Ordinance</hi> play, and <hi>bullets</hi> fly thicke about their cares. And certainely there is nothing in the world more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pitifull; an <hi>Ape carrier</hi> is honourable compared with a Drunkard: and hear but their wives ſpeake, you will grant that his of the two is farre more happy in her choiſe.</p>
            <p>Yea, Drunkards are ſo unworthy the meaneſt repute, that by the law, they ought to be <hi>ſtoued to death, Deut.</hi> 21.20, 21. and by the Goſpell, to bee ſpurned or ſpued out of other mens company; I meane <hi>ſeparated from all Chriſtian ſociety,</hi> and like dirt throwne out of the Church into the ſtreet, by excommunication, as is commanded, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. And untill that rule be obſerved, we ſhall have but a ſorry reformation. For are they not as excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and had <hi>humors</hi> in mans <hi>body;</hi> which is never at eaſe till it be there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of disburdened? as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes do they not infect all that converſe with them? Is not the <hi>Goſpel and the name of God blaſphemed among the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles?</hi> and an evill ſcandall raiſed upon the whole Church through their ſuperlative wickedneſſe? <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.24. does not their unchriſtian-like behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our cauſe the very Turkes even to deteſt the true religion, and proteſt againſt their owne converſion? thinking it impoſſible that he ſhould be a good God, who hath ſuch evill ſonnes.</p>
            <p>And ſure I am, that in the <hi>Primitive</hi> times, the Church would have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ied her bleſſing to ſuch ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> as theſe are, who make a trade of ſinne; as though there were no God to judge, nor hell to puniſh, nor hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to reward; and live as if they had no ſoules to ſave. Such as have ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151474:16"/>out of their hearts the <hi>feare of Ged,</hi> the <hi>ſhame of the world,</hi> the <hi>love of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and the <hi>dread of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el;</hi> not caring what is thought, or ſpoken of them here; or what becomes of them hereafter. Yea ſuch amonſtrous menſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous brood, that (like a certaine mountaine in <hi>Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bia</hi>) breed, and bring forth nothing but <hi>monſters;</hi> whoſe deeds are too foule for my words to expreſſe; being ſuch as <hi>ought not to bee</hi> once <hi>named amongſt Chriſtians, Epheſians</hi> 5.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Now the good husbandman <hi>weeds</hi> his <hi>field of burtfull plants;</hi> that they may not ſpoile the good <hi>corne;</hi> and when fire hath taken a <hi>houſe,</hi> we uſe to pull it downe, leſt it ſhould fire alſo the neighbours houſes: Yea the good <hi>Chirurgeon</hi> cuts off a rotten <hi>member</hi> betimes, that the ſound may not be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered.</p>
            <p>§ 22. And thus I have made it good, that Drunkards drinke not for ſtrength, but luſt, and pride; to ſhew how full of Satan they be, and how neare to Swine. And that their chiefe delight, is to make men drinke theſe healths till they vomit up their ſhame againe li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e a filthy <hi>dog,</hi> or lye wallowing in their beaſtlineſs like a brutiſh <hi>ſwine,</hi> and make it their onely glory; which is the moſt ſad, and wofull ſpectacle to a rectified underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that can be. Yea they will brag of the conqueſt, when with the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of full charged cups, they have overcome the reſt: which is the baſeſt office, and lamentableſt overthrow to themſelves that can poſſibly be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. For what a barbarous, graceleſs, and unchriſtian-like practice is this? to take pleaſure in making others drunke, as if it were their glory and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtime to ſee <hi>God diſhonoured, his ſpirit grieved, his name blaſphemed, his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures abuſed,</hi> themſelves and their friends ſoules <hi>damned.</hi> But ſurely to glory in giving weake braines a drench, to ſee them wallow in their filthineſſe, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but to brag how far they are become the Devils children. Yea, ſuch men clime the higheſt ſtep of the ladder of wickedneſs; thinking their owne fin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will not preſs them deep enough into hell, except they alſo load themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with other mens; for this is no other then the ſetting a mans own houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fire, it burnes many of his neighbours, and he ſhall anſwer for all the ruines.</p>
            <p>§ 23. But ſee their cunning, and induſtry in tempting to ſin, and drawing to perdition. A drunkard (as if his brains were fired with all the plots, projects, and cunning ſtratagems that hel can yeeld) is as rarely gifted in drawing to ſin, as the Devil himſelf; and is become the child of hel by as proper a right: ſo that if Satan would change his office, or were to ſurrender his place to any man alive, it ſhould be to ſome good fellow or other; who hath learned to han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle a man ſo ſweetly, that one would think it a pleaſure to be ſeduced. For to take away all ſuſpition, they will ſo mollifie the ſtifneſs of a mans pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, ſo temper and fit him to their owne mould; that once to doith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would require the ſpirit of diſcerning. As how many are there that hate their other enemies, yea and their friends too; and yet embrace this ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, becauſe he kiſſeth when he betrayeth? As what fence for the <hi>Piſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that is charged with the <hi>Bulle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of friendſhip? <hi>Hilary</hi> compares it to a <hi>Razo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:151474:17"/>in the hand of a counterfeit Barber. And indeed he ſo confirmeth the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of his love, with vowes, proteſtations, and promiſes, (as a large complement for the moſt part uſhers in a cloſe craft) that you would thinke <hi>Jonathans</hi> love to <hi>David,</hi> was nothing in compariſon (as no faces looke love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier then the painred) but accept of gaine from him, and you are loſt for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. For with <hi>Siſera,</hi> you can no ſooner taſte of this <hi>Jaels milke,</hi> but you ſhall feel a <hi>naile</hi> in your Temples. So that the very wickedneſs of one which feareth God, is better then the good intreaty of a Drunkard. His prof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers are like the <hi>Fowlers ſhrape,</hi> when he caſts meat to <hi>Birds:</hi> which is not out of charity to relieve, but out of treachery to enſnare them.</p>
            <p>Or like <hi>Traps</hi> we ſet for vermine; which ſeem charitable when they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to kill. <hi>They lay wait,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ieremy, as he that ſetteth ſnares; and make a pit to catch men, Ier.</hi> 5.26. and thou mayeſt anſwer theſe curſed tempters which delight in the murther of ſoules, as the woman of <hi>Endor</hi> did <hi>Saul, wherefore ſeekeſt thou to take me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in a ſnare, to cauſe me to dye?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.9. Or as a Godly woman (ſpoken of by <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) did one that ſollicited her to incontinency, profeſſing how infinitely he loved her: who anſwered him, If you love me ſo well as you profeſs, or ſeem to do, hold your finger in this flame untill the fleſh be burnt off; and when he anſwered that was no part of love in her to require it: ſhe replyed yes, if yours be love to cauſe both my body and ſoule to burne in hell fire for ever; which by conſequence will follow if I yeeld to your requeſt, and follow your counſel. And to ſpeak right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this is the depth of a Drunkards love; and yet never ſuch abject, and ſervile proſtitutions of preſentations: as <hi>life, ſoule, devotion, adoration, ſervant, ſtave &amp;c.</hi> as there is among. Drunkards. Oh will one drunkard ſay, (yea ſweare) to another, I love thee as well as my ſelfe, and therein ſpeak truth: for what ſaid <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to ſuch an one? <hi>Thou loveſt thy ſelfe ſo, as thou wilt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thy ſelfe; and thou wilt deſtroy him, whom thou loveſt as thy ſelfe.</hi> To ſum up all, in briefe, A drunkard for kindneſs is another <hi>Iulian,</hi> who was often times b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> untifull, but how? he never did a man a good turne, but it was to dainne his ſoule. He is another <hi>Abſalom,</hi> who made a feaſt for <hi>Amnen,</hi> whom he meant to kill.</p>
            <p>§ 24. Which is the ſole cauſe, that drunkards ſwarme ſo in every corner of the Land; as where ſhall a man come, and not finde one of theſe ſeducers? Yea whole herds of them? as were I injoined to take up a ragged Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I ſhould thinke it no hard taske, to muſter up a thouſand men, (admit but drunkards to be men) out of the very Suburbs, that in ſheere drinke, ſpend all they can <hi>get, borrow,</hi> or <hi>imbezill.</hi> Indeed heretofore they were as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>are as <hi>Wolves,</hi> but now they are as common as <hi>Hogs.</hi> Heretofore it was the ſinne of <hi>Tinkers, Hoſtlers, Beggers, &amp;c.</hi> now of <hi>Farmers, Citizens, Eſquires, Knights, &amp;c.</hi> Heretofore wine was ſold onely in Apothecaries ſhops, and drunke rather in time of ſickneſſe, then in health: now it's vented in Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes, as if it grew in the <hi>Thames.</hi> There was a ſtreet in <hi>Rome</hi> called <hi>Vicus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obrius,</hi> Sober ſtreet; becauſe there was never a drinking houſe in it. Finde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch a ſtreet in any <hi>City,</hi> or populous <hi>Towne</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and ſome good man
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151474:17"/>or other, will put it in the Chronicle. Yea woe is me! how is the world turned <hi>Beaſt?</hi> what <hi>bowſing,</hi> and <hi>quaffing,</hi> and <hi>whiffing,</hi> and <hi>healthing,</hi> is there on every <hi>bench?</hi> and what <hi>reeling,</hi> and <hi>ſtaggering</hi> in our ſtreets? what drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by the <hi>yard,</hi> the <hi>dye,</hi> the <hi>dozen?</hi> what forcing of <hi>pledges?</hi> what quarrels for <hi>meaſure</hi> and <hi>forme?</hi> how is that become an excuſe of villany, which any villany might rather excuſe I <hi>was drunke?</hi> how hath this <hi>torrent,</hi> yea this <hi>deluge</hi> of exceſs in drinke, drowned the face of the earth, and riſen many cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits above the higheſt Mountaines of Religion and good Lawes? Yea would to God I might not ſay (that which I feare, and ſhame, and grieve to ſay) that even ſome of them which ſquare the Arke for others, inwardly drowne themſelves, and diſcover their nakedneſs hereby. That other inundation ſcowred the world, this impures it: and what but a <hi>deluge</hi> of <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone,</hi> can waſh it from ſo abominable filthineſs?</p>
            <p>O the drunkenneſs that is in one day in this <hi>Land!</hi> yea in this <hi>City!</hi> yea at ſome <hi>fair</hi> or <hi>market</hi> to be ſeen! for goe but to the Towns end where a Fair is kept; and there they lie as if ſome <hi>field</hi> had beene <hi>fought;</hi> here lyes one man, there another; yea alas for woe, a womannay aſwine with a womans face. Or goe into the back lanes, and there you ſhall have them among Frogs and Toads, their fit matches. To be ſhort, it is a diſeaſe whereof this Nation and Generation is ſicke at the very heart; and which is worſe, in all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability this infectious vice of drunken good-fellowſhip is like to ſtick by this Nation: for ſo long as the <hi>mulutude of offenders, benums the ſenſe of offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;</hi> a common blor is held no ſtaine.</p>
            <p>§ 25. Increaſe it may, as how can it other? when each Drunkard is like the bramble, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9.15. which firſt ſet it ſelfe on fire, and then <hi>fired all the wood.</hi> Or like one ſicke of the Plague, who (as they ſay) is carryed with an itching deſire to infect others that are cleere. Or like an houſe on <hi>fire</hi> in the midſt of a City; which (if the winde blowes vehemently) ſtayeth not in the burning of an houſe or two, but ſets on fire all adjoining: neither doth it ceaſe there, but every one which it hath ſet on fire kindles as many more, and ſo one another til it may be half, or all the whole City be conſumed. For this is the Drunkards caſe directly, who is the bane of many poore ſouls beſides his owne. It is <hi>Baſils</hi> obſervation, that <hi>one whore makes many fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors:</hi> but experience ſhewes, that one drunkard makes ten times as many drunkards.</p>
            <p>As what a multitude of drunkards, will one true drunkard make; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if hee be well accompliſhed with ingenuity, and gifts of nature? As when <hi>Achitophels</hi> head ſtands upon <hi>Simon Magus</hi> his ſhoulders, there is a world of miſchiefe towards. A <hi>will</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent to do harm, and a <hi>wit</hi> able to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute it, like <hi>Cannon ſhot,</hi> makes a lane where it goes.</p>
            <p>All which conſidered, <hi>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> the number of <hi>ſeducers,</hi> together with their <hi>skill, will,</hi> and <hi>induſtry in ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ng:</hi> we may with reverence, and love, wonder at the mercy of <hi>God</hi> in our delivery. For as our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed is the man that is not offended at their ſcoffes,</hi> Mat. 11.6. ſo bleſſed is the man, that is not taken with their wils. For herein alone conſiſts the difference; <hi>He whom
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151474:18"/>the Lord loves, ſhall be delivered</hi> from their meretricious allurements, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 2.26. and he <hi>whom the Lord abhors,</hi> ſhall fall into their ſnares, <hi>Prov.</hi> 22.14. And ſo much of the Drunkards ſubtilty in ſeducing.</p>
            <p>§ 26. Now if they cannot <hi>allure</hi> and <hi>perſwade</hi> men to pledge them in their wicked cuſtoms; and ſo worke their wils by <hi>ſubtilty</hi> and <hi>faire meanes;</hi> they will ſeeke to <hi>compell</hi> and <hi>enforce</hi> them to do as they do: that ſo they may have their company here <hi>in ſin,</hi> and hereafter <hi>in torment.</hi> At leaſt that they may diſcourage us in the way to heaven; <hi>floute</hi> us out of our faith; and <hi>draw</hi> us backe to the world: when they can no longer ſeduce us, they will <hi>envy, bate, cenſure, ſcoffe</hi> at, <hi>revile, rail</hi> on, <hi>nickname, ſlander</hi> falſly, <hi>accuſe, curſe, threaten, undermine, and combine</hi> together againſt us: Yea did not the Law manacle their hands, they would even <hi>ſtrike, hurt,</hi> and <hi>ſlay</hi> us; in caſe we would not yet yeeld to aſſociate them in their evill doings, nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme to their lewd and wicked cuſtomes; If we would not for company grievouſly ſinne againſt God, wrong our owne <hi>bodies,</hi> deſtroy our <hi>ſoules,</hi> and wilfully leap into <hi>Hell fire</hi> with them. They would make us ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>bow,</hi> or <hi>breake;</hi> they would kill our <hi>bodies,</hi> if they could not corrupt our <hi>ſoules.</hi> If we would not part with our <hi>innocency,</hi> we ſhould part with our <hi>lives:</hi> as it fared with thoſe numberleſs <hi>Martyrs, whoſe ſoules</hi> 8. <hi>Iohn ſaw under the Altar, Rev.</hi> 6. who were <hi>killed</hi> becauſe they would not do and ſay at the reſt; yea even <hi>for the word of God, and for the teſtimony which they main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, ver.</hi> 9. And why fares it not ſo with us? why do not the ſame drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, vitious livers, and other enemies of holineſs, which now <hi>envy, hate, cenſure, ſcoffe</hi> at, <hi>nickname, raile</hi> on, and <hi>ſlander</hi> us; even <hi>ſtrike, maime,</hi> and <hi>kill</hi> us? but becauſe their <hi>hands</hi> are tyed by the Law. Why are not our <hi>Sanctuaries</hi> turned into <hi>ſhambles,</hi> and our <hi>beds</hi> made to ſwimme with our <hi>bloods,</hi> in <hi>London</hi> (as it fares with them in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and in many parts of this kingdome) long before this? but that the God of <hi>Iſrael</hi> hath croſſed the confederacy of <hi>Balak.</hi> It is no thankes to wicked men, that their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs doth not proſper: they have laid a world of plots, ever ſince there was a purpoſe of <hi>Reformation,</hi> to <hi>cut</hi> all the <hi>Roundheads throats,</hi> had not <hi>juſtice</hi> and an over-ruling <hi>providence</hi> prevented them. The world would ſoone be over-runne with evils, if men might be ſo devilliſh as they would. Alas if it were not for the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> (for all they are ſo hated, ſcorned, and contemned,) it would be otherwiſe then it is with the People of God; as the <hi>Word</hi> of God, and both <hi>former</hi> and <hi>late</hi> experience do witneſs. But of this, ſee more in the <hi>Drunkards Character:</hi> for I muſt bee briefe. I paſſe therefore from the drunkards qualities, carriage, and behaviour, with the method he uſeth in drinking, to the <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>effects</hi> of their <hi>drunkenneſſe,</hi> which are many. I'le mention ſome only. And</p>
            <p>§ 27. Firſt, I will ſay open the Drunkards outward bodily <hi>deformities;</hi> which are ſundry, and thoſe odious: for commonly he hath (<hi>Vertumnus</hi>-like) a Braſill <hi>noſe,</hi> a ſwolne and inflamed <hi>face;</hi> beſet with goodly <hi>chowles</hi> and <hi>ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies,</hi> as if it were both roſte and ſodde; ſwimming, running, glaring, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle <hi>eyes,</hi> bleered, rowling, and red; a <hi>mouth</hi> naſty, with offenſive fumes,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:151474:18"/>alwayes foaming or drivelling; a feaveriſh <hi>body,</hi> a ſicke and giddy <hi>braine,</hi> a <hi>minde</hi> diſperſed, a boyling <hi>ſtomach,</hi> rotten <hi>teeth,</hi> a ſtinking <hi>breath,</hi> a drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming <hi>eare,</hi> a palſied <hi>hand,</hi> gowty, ſtaggering <hi>legs,</hi> that faine would goe, but cannot: a drawling, ſtammering; temulentive <hi>tongue,</hi> clam'd to the roofe and gums: In fine (not to ſpeake of his odious <hi>geſtures,</hi> loathſome <hi>naſtineſſe,</hi> or beaſtly <hi>behaviour;</hi> his <hi>belching, hiccocks, vomitings;</hi> his ridiculous <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures,</hi> and how eaſily he is knock'd downe, whoſe <hi>hamſtrings Bacchus</hi> hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready cut in two: nor of the unmeaſurable groſſeneſs of ſuch, whoſe only Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is <hi>Ale;</hi> eſpecially your <hi>Alewives,</hi> who like the <hi>Germane Froes</hi> are all <hi>cheekes</hi> to the <hi>belly,</hi> and all <hi>belly</hi> to the <hi>knees;</hi> whoſe <hi>dugs</hi> and <hi>chinnes</hi> meet without any forcing of either: becauſe you may dayly ſee ſuch fuſtilugs walking in the ſtreets, like ſo many <hi>Tunnes,</hi> each moving upon two <hi>pottle pots</hi>) His eſſentiall parts are ſo obſcured; his <hi>ſenſe</hi> ſo dulled, his <hi>eyes</hi> ſo dazelled, his <hi>face</hi> ſo diſtorted, his <hi>countenance</hi> ſo deformed, his <hi>joints</hi> ſo infeebled, and his whole <hi>body</hi> and <hi>minde</hi> ſo transformed; that he is become the childe of folly, the deriſion of the world, a laughing ſtock to <hi>fooles,</hi> a laothing ſtock to the <hi>godly,</hi> ridiculous to all. Yea queſtionleſſe, had they a glaſs preſented them, they could hardly be brought againe to love their owne faces. Much more ſhould they read a true Character of their odious conditions; would they run beſides their wits, if they had any to loſe; or goe and diſpatch themſelves as <hi>Bepalus</hi> did upon view of <hi>Hipponax</hi> his <hi>letter.</hi> For (<hi>Therſites</hi>-like) many are their bodily deformities; but farre more, and worſe are thoſe of their ſoules.</p>
            <p>§ 28. Neither are his <hi>diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>infirmities</hi> fewer then his <hi>deformities:</hi> for exceſſive and intemperate drinking, hath brought upon him a world of diſeaſes and infirmities which ſhorten his life; as who can recount, or recite the <hi>crudities, rheumes, gowtes, dropſies, aches, impoſthumes, apoplexies, inflammati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, pluriſies, conſumptions,</hi> (for though he devoures much, yet he is the leaner every way) with the <hi>falling ſickneſſe,</hi> and innumerable other <hi>diſtempers</hi> hence enſuing; which drunkards better know by experience, then I how to reckon up?</p>
            <p>To whom are <hi>pearled faces, palſies, head-aches,</hi> but to Drunkards? what ſo much as ſwilling, blowes up the <hi>cheekes</hi> with wind; fils the <hi>noſe</hi> and <hi>eyes</hi> with fire; loads the <hi>hands</hi> and <hi>legs</hi> with water; and in ſhort plagues the whole man with the diſeaſes of an <hi>Horſe,</hi> the belly of a <hi>Cow,</hi> the head of an <hi>Aſſe,</hi> &amp;c. almoſt turning him into a very <hi>walking dunghill?</hi> Beleeve a man in his owne art, the diſtempered body, the more it is filled, the more it is ſpilled, ſaith <hi>Hippocrates;</hi> and to it the Prophet ſets his ſeal, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 7.5. ſo that the Drunkard drawes death out of that which preſerves other mens lives; and the reaſon is, the naturall, and vitall <hi>heat</hi> of men is hereby drowned, and extinguiſhed before it be neere ſpent; like a candle caſt into the <hi>water,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be halfe <hi>burnt.</hi> Yea wine, and ſtrong drinke hath drowned more men then the Sea hath devoured; and more dye of <hi>ſurfets</hi> then by the <hi>ſword.</hi> Yea as drunkenneſs hath drowned more <hi>ſoules</hi> then all the ſinnes of <hi>Sodomes</hi> ſo it hath drowned more <hi>bodies,</hi> then were drowned in the generall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151474:19"/>of <hi>Noabs flood:</hi> But you have not heard all; for,</p>
            <p>§ 29. Thirdly, as if the drunkard ſcorned to goe to his grave in peace, he ſtrives to do execution upon himſelfe: either by drinking untill his skin and guts cracke againe: As how many have dranke themſelves dead? how many have even burſt themſelves with drinking, and ſo dyed? being taken away in Gods juſt wrath, &amp;c. Or ſecondly, by a frequent expoſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the darke, to divers fearfull and lamentable accidents: whereby he oft breakes his <hi>limbes,</hi> or <hi>necke; drownes or burnes</hi> himſelfe. Yea how oft have <hi>ſnakes</hi> beene knowne to creepe downe their <hi>throats</hi> into their <hi>bellies,</hi> as they lay aſleep in the fields? And how ſhould it be otherwiſe? for when he is drunk, he is like a running <hi>Coach</hi> without a <hi>Coachman</hi> to guide it, as <hi>Pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacus</hi> makes the compariſon. Or thirdly, by running into quarreſs when hee is drunke; whereby he either murthers others, or is ſtabbed, and murthered by others. For while the wine workes, they reſemble thoſe <hi>fiſhes</hi> which love to be in violent <hi>ſtreames,</hi> and <hi>flood gates;</hi> but do dye in <hi>ſtill waters.</hi> As who will ſooner kil and ſlay then <hi>Cowards,</hi> when once they are <hi>pot</hi> valiant? I deny not, but ſuch a ones diſcourſe may ſometimes ſound big, and yet mean nothing: Cowards being moſt forward both in giving <hi>charge with the tongue, and recoyling back with the foot.</hi> Yea you ſhal ſee a drunkard look like the foure <hi>windes in painting;</hi> as if he would blow away the <hi>enemy;</hi> and yet at the very firſt onſet, ſuffer <hi>feare,</hi> and <hi>trembling</hi> to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs themſelves in his <hi>face</hi> apparently. And commonly where is leaſt <hi>heart,</hi> there is moſt <hi>tongue:</hi> ſwelling words being like the <hi>report of great Ordnance;</hi> which doth only <hi>blaze,</hi> and <hi>cracke,</hi> and <hi>ſmoake,</hi> and <hi>ſtinke,</hi> and <hi>vaniſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this holdes not alwayes, for ſure I am, many do that in a Taverne, which they repent at Tiburne; and nothing more common then for drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards to <hi>kiſſe when they meet,</hi> and <hi>kill when they part.</hi> For when they have loſt the ſterne of reaſon, it ſhall goe hard, but they will either give <hi>offence,</hi> or take it. A drunken man you know, will make a fray with his owne ſhadow; or ſuppoſe he but nods his head againſt ſome <hi>Poſt</hi> or <hi>Table,</hi> (for they will even fall aſleepe as they ſit) he is ſo ſtupefied, that in revenge he will ſtrike his oppoſite for the wrong, and then call for drinke to make himſelfe friends againe: which friendly cup, gives occaſion of a ſecond quarrell; for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he laughes or chafes, he is alike apt to quarrell. Or let but a friend admoniſh him, hee were as good take a Beare by the tooth.</p>
            <p>This ſinne ſcorns reproofe, admonition to it were like <hi>goads</hi> to them that are mad already: or like powring <hi>oyle</hi> downe the chimney, which may ſet the houſe on <hi>fire,</hi> but never abate the <hi>heat;</hi> it may move them to choler, never to amendment. I am loath to trouble you with the multitude of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples which are recorded of thoſe, that having made up the meaſure of their wickeneſſe; have <hi>Amnon</hi>-like dyed, and been ſlaine in Drinke, as it were with the weapon in their belly, being taken away in Gods juſt wrath: it faring with them as it did with that <hi>Pope,</hi> whom the Devill is ſaid to have ſlaine in the very inſtant of his <hi>adultery,</hi> and carry him quicke to hell. And
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:151474:19"/>what can be more fearefull, then when their <hi>heads</hi> are <hi>merry,</hi> and their <hi>wits drowned</hi> with wine, to be ſuddenly ſtricken with death: as if the exccu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were no leſſe intended to the <hi>ſcule,</hi> then to the <hi>body?</hi> or what can be more juſt, then that they which in many years impunity, will finde no lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of repentance, ſhould at laſt receive a puniſhment, without poſſibility of repentance? But</p>
            <p>§ 30. Fourthly, as drunkenneſſe is the <hi>cauſe of murther,</hi> ſo it is no leſſe the <hi>cauſe of Adultery:</hi> You ſhall rarely (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) ſee a man <hi>continent</hi> that is not <hi>abſtinent.</hi> Yea (ſaith <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) the firſt evill of drunkenneſſe, is danger of chaſtity; for <hi>Bacchus</hi> is but a pandar to <hi>Venus;</hi> as one Devill is ready to helpe another in miſchiefe. <hi>He that tarrieth long at the wine,</hi> ſaith Solomon, <hi>his eyes ſhall looke upon ſtrange women, and his heart ſhall ſpeake lewd things. Prov.</hi> 23.33. And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth that the <hi>fruits of gluttony and drunkenneſſe, is chambering and wantonneſſe, Rom.</hi> 13.13. And the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Lot,</hi> more then proves it, who being ſober, abhorred all filthineſs; but being drunke he was eaſily drawne to commit <hi>inceſt with his owne daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; not once perceiving when he lay downe, or when he roſe up. Gen.</hi> 19.32. to 36. Which being rightly conſidered, methinkes a man had need to bee drunke before hand, that ſhall admit of more wine then enough; that ſhall for one <hi>howers</hi> mad <hi>mirth,</hi> hazard a whole <hi>age</hi> of <hi>griefe</hi> and <hi>ſhame;</hi> together with his diſpleaſure, that is <hi>able to deſtroy both body and ſoul in hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You know when <hi>Iron</hi> is <hi>hot,</hi> the Smith can faſhion it to his pleaſure; and wine tempers the heart like wax for the Devils impreſſion. When a man is drunk, Satan may ſtampe in his heart the fouleſt ſin; but luſt will admit no deniall. That heat which is taken at the <hi>Tavern</hi> muſt be allayed at the <hi>Brothel houſe.</hi> And the blood which is fired with <hi>Bacchus,</hi> muſt be cooled with <hi>Venus.</hi> Yea the Devil ſhould forget both his office, and malice, if he did not play the Pandar to concupiſcence this way: for <hi>idleneſſe</hi> makes way for <hi>looſe compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> looſe company makes way for <hi>wine,</hi> wine makes way for <hi>luſt,</hi> and luſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>worke for the Devill: Venus</hi> comes out of the <hi>froth</hi> of this <hi>Sea.</hi> Nor d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſtity ever ſleep in a Drunkards bed.</p>
            <p>The Drunkard is like a <hi>Salamander ſtone,</hi> which <hi>fires</hi> at the ſight of every flame. Yea if he but ſee a <hi>whore,</hi> and ſhe him; like the <hi>Weeſle,</hi> and the <hi>Baſiliske,</hi> they poiſon each o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her with their ſight, <hi>Prev.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p>Wine and high dyet, is adulteries nurſe: <hi>They roſe up in the morning like fed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſes</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) and what followes? <hi>Every man neighed after his neighbours wiſe; Ier.</hi> 5.8. which is more then true with our Drunkards; who like the Horſe &amp; Mule, that have no underſtanding, no ſhame, no conſcience, &amp;c. eſpecially your <hi>brazen</hi> brained, and <hi>flinty</hi> foreheaded clownes; can no ſooner ſpye a woman or maid even in the open ſtreets, but they will fall to embracing and tempting her with ribauldry, ſcurrility, and turning every word ſhe ſpeakes, to ſome laſcivious and obſcene ſenſe; whereof they are not a little proud; though it would make a wiſe and modeſt man even ſpue to heare them.</p>
            <p>Now what hath beene ſaid of Murther and Adultery, may alſo be aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151474:20"/>of <hi>every other ſinne</hi> that can be named: for what ſinne was there ever committed, which wine hath not proved the occaſion of? as our <hi>reverend Judges,</hi> in their ſeverall circuits, finde by continued experience? but I muſt paſſe over many things</p>
            <p>§ 31. Fiftly, as the drunkard deformes his <hi>body,</hi> impaires his <hi>health,</hi> ſhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens his <hi>life,</hi> &amp;c. by his exceſſive drinking: ſo he conſumes his eſtate, and brings himſelfe to poverty, and want, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſhewes, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.21. And I could largely demonſtrate how they conſume their wealth at the wine, even untill they have ſwallowed downe their whole eſtates: and then rather then not ſatisfie their guts, that they will ſpend in ſheere drinke, all the cloathes on their beds and backs. Yea they will drinke the very blood of their <hi>wives</hi> and <hi>children;</hi> who are not onely <hi>impoveriſhed,</hi> but even <hi>parched</hi> with famine, and <hi>burnt</hi> up with thirſt, to ſatisfie his throat; in which hee is worſe then an <hi>Infidell,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. But I will paſs this, as of leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence. Only obſerve how he is paid in his owne coine. The Drunkard having ſpent all in ſuperfluities, in the end he wants neceſſaries; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in his youth he will drinke nothing but <hi>wine,</hi> in his old age he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to drinke <hi>water.</hi> Yea how oft are <hi>Vermine</hi> ſeene to ſuck his bloud, as faſt as he doth that of the <hi>grape</hi> and <hi>mauli?</hi> And laſtly, how he throwes his <hi>houſe</hi> ſo long out at <hi>windowes,</hi> that at laſt his <hi>houſe</hi> throwes him out at <hi>doores:</hi> and when all is gone, glad would he be to be a <hi>Swine-herd</hi> like the <hi>prodigall ſonne:</hi> but knowing himſelfe unworthy of any mans entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he growes weary of his life, and is ready to make himſelfe away; like <hi>Peter</hi> the Cardinall, baſe ſon to <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth, that monſtrous Epicure, the ſhame of the later times; or like <hi>Apicius,</hi> the ſhame of the ancient age wherein he lived. Neither ſtayes he here, for the tiplers <hi>progreſſe</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly from <hi>luxury</hi> to <hi>beggery;</hi> from beggery to <hi>theevery;</hi> from the Taverne to Tiburne; from the Alehouſe to the Gallows.</p>
            <p>§ 32. Againe, ſixtly, another effect of drunkenneſs is, it not onely cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth a world of vaine <hi>babling,</hi> ſcurilous <hi>jeſting,</hi> wicked <hi>talking,</hi> impious <hi>ſwearing,</hi> &amp;c. as I have already ſhewen; but over and above, it mightily decayes the <hi>braine;</hi> for if it findes them not <hi>fooles,</hi> it makes them <hi>fooles</hi> that follow it. Indeed for the moſt part it findes men fooles; for exceſs is a true argument of folly; as who more fooliſh then thoſe prophane <hi>Eſaus,</hi> that will ſell their <hi>birthright, reaſon,</hi> and the bleſſing of <hi>grace</hi> here, and <hi>glory</hi> hereafter, for a <hi>meſſe of pottage;</hi> a little ſenſuall delight: and with <hi>Adam</hi> part with their ſalvations for an <hi>Apple?</hi> What greater folly, and madneſs, ſaith <hi>Gregory,</hi> then for a little tickling of the palat, a kinde of running banquet: to loſe an <hi>eternall Kingdome,</hi> and expoſe ones ſelfe to <hi>a devouring fire, an everlaſting burning? Eſay</hi> 33.14. Surely in this caſe, if a man were not either fooliſh, or drunke before hand, he could never yeeld to be made drunke. But ſecondly, if they have wit, and other good naturall parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, yet this vice makes them become fooles. Yea, it is the funerall of all a mans good parts. For drunkenneſs baniſheth wit; reaſon is ſo clowded with thoſe fogs, and miſts, which aſcend up out of the kitchen of the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151474:20"/>to the braine, that their wits runne a wool-gathering, as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is.</p>
            <p>A full <hi>belly</hi> makes an empty <hi>braine,</hi> when a maſſe of moiſture (like the firſt <hi>Chaos</hi>) is in the ſtomach; all the faculties of the ſoule are void, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out forme; and darkneſs is upon the face of it; untill there be another <hi>Fiat</hi> even a voice from heaven commanding a new light.</p>
            <p>Yea drunkenneſs <hi>beſots</hi> the ſtrongeſt braine, and <hi>beſtiates</hi> even the braveſt ſpirits: when the Grecians that ſage Nation, fell to this vice, they mightily decayed in braine. And take this for a rule, while <hi>Bacchus</hi> is a mans chiefe God, <hi>Apollo</hi> will never keepe him company. I name not theſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit deities to grace, but rather to diſgrace them.</p>
            <p>Neither are men rob'd by it of their naturall parts onely, but drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs darkens the light both of <hi>nature,</hi> and <hi>grace;</hi> and ſo yeelds men over unto Satan, to be led by him, as it were <hi>blind-fold</hi> into all manner of ſinne, and wickedneſs. And which is moſt remarkeable, this may ſeeme to bee the drunkards aime: for being at it, he will never give over drinking, till hee hath laid <hi>Reaſon</hi> his <hi>keeper</hi> to <hi>ſleep,</hi> and blown out that little <hi>light</hi> which is left in him, and deſperately drowned the voice, and cry of Conſcience.</p>
            <p>§ 33. And the like touching Memory; for the abundance of wine hath drowned and mudded that noble Recorder. The drunkard firſt ſpeakes hee knowes not what; nor after can he remember what that was he ſpake. A Drunkards <hi>minde,</hi> and <hi>ſtomach</hi> are alike: neither can <hi>retaine</hi> what they <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive; deep drinkers</hi> have <hi>ſhallow me mories.</hi> Yea drunkenneſs takes from men wit, memory, and all other their good parts: as how many of theſe <hi>quagmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts,</hi> have loſt their ſouls ſight by overmuch drinking; as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> did his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily? How many through a long cuſtome in this vice, are growne ſottiſh, and ſtupid, as if their <hi>braines</hi> were buried in <hi>tar?</hi> I ſpeake not of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time onely, when they are in drinke; for then I ſhould tell you of one drunkard, that ſought all the Innes in the Towne for his <hi>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe,</hi> when indeed he came thither on <hi>foot:</hi> of another that having laid his <hi>brecches</hi> under his bed, for the more ſafety of his <hi>purſe;</hi> challenged the Chamberlaine that he had ſtolne them away: of a third, that ſtuft his <hi>pillow</hi> (a braſs <hi>pot</hi>) with <hi>ſtraw</hi> to make it ſoft: of a fourth, that fell to cuſſing of a <hi>poſt,</hi> for not giving him the wall; and being told that it was a <hi>poſt,</hi> made reply, he might have blowne his <hi>horne</hi> then. I might alſo tell you, how a <hi>Taverne</hi> was by the fancy and imagination of a drunken crue, turned into a <hi>Galley:</hi> who having a <hi>tempeſt</hi> in their heads, cauſed by a <hi>Sea of drinke</hi> within; verily thought this Taphouſe on <hi>land,</hi> a Pinnace at <hi>Sea;</hi> and the preſent ſtorme ſo vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that they unloaded the <hi>Ship,</hi> throwing the goods out at <hi>window,</hi> inſtead of <hi>overboard;</hi> calling the Conſtable <hi>Neptune,</hi> and the Officers <hi>Tritons:</hi> Whereupon ſome got under the Table, as if they lay under Hatches, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holding a great <hi>pot</hi> for the <hi>Maſt;</hi> all crying out that ſo many brave gentlemen ſhould be <hi>caſt away,</hi> as <hi>Atheneus</hi> relates; with abundance of the like, did they not tend rather to laughter, then godly edifying: but I ſpeak of habituated drunkards, when they are at the beſt.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:151474:21"/>
            <p>I confeſs, it is the better for them that they are fools, the caſe being right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered; for what <hi>Owen</hi> ſpeaks in the Epigram, may be applyed to ſundry Drunkards;</p>
            <q>
               <l>Good wine they ſay makes vinegar moſt tart:</l>
               <l>Thou the more witty, the more wicked art.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Yea had they been borne meere naturals, they had either been in no fault, or in a great deale leſſe fault then they are. And ſo you ſee that drunkards are ſtrangely ſtupendious, and forgetfull; that drunkenneſs deprives men both of wit and memory: and yet they madly purſue this vice, as the kindler of them. But no wonder, when the forbidden <hi>Tree,</hi> which promiſed our firſt <hi>Parents</hi> knowledge, tooke their knowledge from them; the ſame Devil having a hand in both.</p>
            <p>§ 34. Thus having got through the principall ſtages of the drunkards progreſs; before we goe any further, let us looke backe upon what we have paſt. As how they imitate their Father the Devill, in tempting, and in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to ſinne, and in drawing to perdition: after a review taken, let any ſtander by ſay, whether Satan be ſo much beholding to any men alive, as to them; whether he hath any ſervants, that do him ſuch faithfull ſervice; any Factors that make him a better returne of ſoules; any <hi>Generals,</hi> that ſubdue ſo many ſouldiers to him; any <hi>advocates,</hi> that pleade ſo hard for him, as the true drunkard. I preſume you cannot nominate one: I confeſs a beautifull <hi>whoriſh woman,</hi> (another of the Devils <hi>lime-twigs</hi>) who hath a <hi>flattering tongue,</hi> Prov. 6.24. <hi>ſmooth and enticing words,</hi> Prov. 7.5. <hi>lips which drop like an hony comb; and a mouth more ſoft then oyle,</hi> Prov. 5.3. does the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill ſingular ſervice in the buſineſs of tempting, for infinite are the ſoules which theſe artificiall Paradiſes have beguiled; for as through an Hell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, God brings many to Heaven; ſo through an Heaven upon Earth many bring themſelves to Hell. And ſhe hath a priviledg above other temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; for <hi>Cockatrice</hi>-like, ſhe killeth with her very ſight: yea ſhe is able to take a man with her very <hi>eyelids, Prov.</hi> 6.25. which makes the Wiſe man ſay, that many have periſhed by the beauty of women, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 9.8. Yet never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, let her bid welcome to all commers; ſo that any baſe fellow may ride her <hi>poſt</hi> to the Devill, with a <hi>golden bit:</hi> thee ſhall never be able to fill hell, (her body will not hold out) nor helpe to people that infernall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as ſome Drunkards do, that are gifted thereafter.</p>
            <p>The which conſidered, together with his other ſinnes of <hi>idleneſſe, epicuriſme, adul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, murther,</hi> his vaine <hi>babling,</hi> ſcurrilous <hi>jeſting,</hi> wicked <hi>talking,</hi> impious <hi>ſwearing, atheiſme,</hi> and the like: (for he hath treble heads to <hi>Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>berus,</hi> that ugly porter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Hell</hi>) proves him the King or chieſe of ſinners; as the Baſilisk is called the King of Serpents. And not only ſhewes them to be children of the Devill, as all unregenerate men are; but to be really metamorphoſed into Devils: as <hi>Lots</hi> wife was really metamorphoſed into a Pillar of <hi>Salt,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> companions into <hi>hogs</hi> and <hi>dogs;</hi> and <hi>Cadmus</hi> with his wife into <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents,</hi> as Poets faine. Yea certainely, if the Devill would change his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties, he would put himſelfe into the perſon, and appropriate to himſelfe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151474:21"/>the very qualities of ſome drunken good fellow: as what thinke you? Is not drunkenneſs the <hi>root</hi> of all evill, and the <hi>rot</hi> of all good? yea is not this a ſinne, which turnes a man wholly into ſinne? and as <hi>Ahab ſold himſelfe to worke wickedneſſe,</hi> ſo doth not the drunkard wholly dedicate, reſigne, ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render, and give himſelfe up to ſerve ſinne, and Satan? his whole imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is onely to drinke, drab, quarrell, ſweare, ſcoffe, ſlander, and ſeduce, as if to ſinne were his trade, and he could do nothing elſe. Like the Devill who was a ſinner from the beginning, a ſinner to the end. Yea he is ſinne in the abſtract, as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes. Neither is that man of <hi>ſinne</hi> (2 <hi>Theſſ</hi> 2.3.) fuller of ſinne then ſuch an one; for if theſe be their words and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, what think you are the ſecrets of their hearts? certainely if all their thoughts did but breake forth into action, they would not come far ſhort of the Devils themſelves. Yea if halfe ſo much were knowne to man, as God knowes of them: how would all drunkards hang downe their heads with ſhame? as what ſtrange monſters would appeare? what ugly, odious, hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous fiends would repreſent themſelves? O what ſwarmes, what litters, what legions of noyſome luſts are couched in the ſtinking ſty of a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards heart! which God onely hath reſerved as a prerogative royall to him ſelfe, exactly to ſearch to the bottome, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9, 10.</p>
            <p>You may marvaile at this which hath beene diſcovered, but you would marvaile much more if all ſhould be told. As I could carry you a great way farther, and yet leave more of him before then behinde. For hee is like ſome putrid Grave, the deeper you dig, the fuller you ſhall finde him both of ſtench and horror. But I am injoined to contract him in a ſheet or two of paper, leſt it ſhould cauſe many to make an end before they begin; as not ſeldome doth a little more writ, cauſe a great deale leſs to be read. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, he who hath a long journey to goe, and but a little time allowed him, muſt make but ſhort baits by the way, and cannot ſtand to take e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ery acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance he meets by the hand. And they that are to paint or print a pitcht field, within the compaſs of a ſmall table; can make but few ſouldiers whole, and compleat; but are faine to ſet down for the moſt, their heads only, or their helmets.</p>
            <p>§ 35. Wherefore, as drunkards have ſeen their ſinne laid open; ſo let them now hearken to their puniſhment: for both by Gods, and mans <hi>Law;</hi> next after indictment and conviction, followes ſentence; and after ſentence is paſt comes execution; if a reprieve or pardon be not ſued out in the interim.</p>
            <p>If there be any of theſe <hi>Antipodes</hi> to God and his kingdome, who like Trees have rooted both head and heart into the earth, and ſet heaven at their heeles: That have in this Treatiſe as in a picture taken a full view of his owne horrid and deteſtable condition; and with <hi>Bupalus</hi> the Painter read the lively character of his odious, and deformed demeanour; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he hath ſeene as in a cleare <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> the ugly face of his foule heart, with thoſe ſpots and wrincles, which otherwiſe he could not have eſpyed, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in himſelfe: and further ſeene, how miſerably Satan hath deluded him,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151474:22"/>and ſhal notwithſtanding perſever in this his brutiſh ſenſuality; and reſolve a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt yeelding; and prefer the humouring of his ſoul, before the ſaving of it; and ſhall thinke it a diſparagement to repent him of his errors: and would rather obſtinately continue in them, then diſclaime them; ſo <hi>ſhutting his eyes that he may not ſee, and ſtopping his eares that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e may not heare, and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his heart that he may not conſider;</hi> preſumptuouſly as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly as <hi>Cain</hi> did, deſperately as <hi>Ahab</hi> did, and blaſphemouſly as <hi>Julian</hi> did, Iet him know that he ſhall ſurely periſh. The reaſon of it is taken out of the Proverbs; an Arrow drawne out of <hi>Solomons</hi> ſententious Quiver. Read the words and tremble; <hi>A man that hardeneth his neck when he is rebuked, ſhall ſuddenly be deſtroyed, and that without remedy,</hi> Prov. 29.1. Yea the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſaith, Prov. 1.24, 25, 26, &amp;c. <hi>Becauſe I have called, and ye refuſed; I have ſtretched out mine hand, and yee would not regard, but deſpiſed all my counſell: I will alſo laugh at your deſtruction, and mocke when your feare cometh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And of this we have ſundry inſtances; The <hi>ſonnes of Ely would not hearken unto, nor obey the voyce of their Father,</hi> why? <hi>becauſe</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>the Lord was determined to deſtroy them,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.25. Their hearts muſt be hardened, that they may be deſtroyed; I <hi>know</hi> (ſaith the Prophet to <hi>Amaziah</hi>) <hi>that God hath determined to deſtroy thee, becauſe thou hoſt done this, and hoſt not obeyed my counſell,</hi> 2 Chron. 25.16, 20.</p>
            <p>O remember, I beſeech you! that there is a day of account, a day of death, a day of judgement comming; wherein the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhall be revealed from heaven with his mighty Angels in ſlaming fire, to render vengeance unto them which obey not his Goſpell, and to puniſh them with everlaſting perdition from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 1.7, 8, 9. Jude 15. at which time thou ſhalt heare him pronounce this fearfull doome, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me yee curſed,</hi> Mat. 25.41. which is an everlaſting departure; not for a day, nor for yeares of dayes, nor for millions of yeares; but for eternity; and that from Chriſt, into thoſe ſcorching <hi>flames of fire and brimſtone, which are prepared for the Devill and his Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>More particularly, conſider how many woes the word of God pronounceth againſt drunkards. As <hi>woe to Drunkards</hi> (ſaith Eſay) <hi>that are mighty to drinke wine; and unto them that are ſtrong to poure in ſtrong drink; that continue drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing untill the wine doth inflame them. Woe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Habakkuk, unto him that giveth his neighbour drink till he be drunken. Woe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, to them that tarry long at the wine, to them that goe and ſeeke mixt wine:</hi> Woe to his body, which is a temporall woe; woe to his ſoule, which is a ſpirituall woe; wee to both body and ſoule, which is an eternall woe. <hi>Howle ye drunkards,</hi> ſaith <hi>Joe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>; weepe ye,</hi> ſaith <hi>S. James. Eſay</hi> 5.22. <hi>Habakkuk</hi> 2.15. <hi>Joel</hi> 1.5. <hi>James</hi> 5.1, 5. Yea, which of Gods ſervants hath not a woe in his mouth, to throw at this ſinne? and every title of this word ſhall be accompliſhed: God will one day hold the cup of vengeance to their lips, and bid them drink their fils. Yea as drunkards are Satans Eldeſt ſonnes; ſo they ſhall have a double portion of vengeance. Whereas riot in the forenoone hath beene merry, in the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoone drunke, at night gone to bed ſtarke mad; in the morning of their
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:151474:22"/>reſurrection, it ſhall riſe ſober into everlaſting ſorrow: they finde not the beginning and progreſs ſo ſweet, as the farewell of it ſhall be bitter. For as ſure as God is in heaven, if they forſake not their ſwilling (which they are no more able to do, then they are able to eat a Rock, the Devill hath ſo beſotted them) they ſhall once pay deare for it, even in a bed of unquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable flames.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not of the many temporall judgements which God brings upon them in this life; though to mention them alone were omni-ſufficient, if they thirſted not after their owne ruine. As I could tell them from <hi>Levit.</hi> 26. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. that all curſes threatned, all temporal plagues and judgements which befal men in this life, are inflicted upon them for ſin, and diſobedience. But I ſpeake of thoſe torments which are both intolerable, and intermina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; which can neither bee indured, nor avoided when once entred into.</p>
            <p>If I ſay you perſevere in this your brutiſh ſenſuality, and wil needs <hi>Dives</hi>-like, drink here without thirſt; you ſhall thirſt hereafter without drinke. Yea though that fire be hot; the thirſt great, and a drop of water bee but a little; yet in this hot fire, and great thirſt, that little drop ſhall be denied you, <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. For know this, that without repentance <hi>Paul</hi> will be found a true Prophet; who ſaith that <hi>No drunkard ſhall ever inherit the Kingdome of Heaven,</hi> 1 Cor. 6.9, 10. And <hi>Eſay</hi> no leſs, who ſaith that <hi>Hel enlargeth it ſelfe for drunkards, and openeth her mouth without meaſure; that all thoſe may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into it, who follow drunkenneſſe,</hi> and prefer the pleaſing of their palats; before the ſaving of their ſoules, <hi>Eſay</hi> 5.11, 14. As they make their belly their God, and their ſhame their glory; ſo damnation ſhall be their end. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. Yea their end is a damnation without end; wickedneſs hath but a time, but the puniſhment of it is beyond all time.</p>
            <p>Neither is the extremity of the pain, inferiour to the perpetuity of it; for the paines and ſuffering of the damned are ten thouſand times more then can be imagined by any heart as deepe as the Sea; and can rather be indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then expreſſed. It is a death never to be painted to the life; no pen nor penſil, nor art, nor heart can comprehend it. Yea if all the Land were Paper, and all the water Inke; every Plant a Pen, and every other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a ready writer; yet they could not ſet down the leaſt piece of the pains of Hell fire: for ſhould we firſt burne off one hand, then another, after that each arme, and ſo all the parts of the body, it were intolerable; yet it is nothing to the burning of body and ſoule in Hell: ſhould wee endure ten thouſand yeares torments in hell, it were much; but nothing to eternity: ſhould we ſuffer one paine, it were enough, but if we come there, our pains for number and kindes, ſhall be infinitely various, as our pleaſures have beene here. Every ſenſe, and member, every power and faculty, both of ſoule and body, ſhall have their ſeverall objects of wretchedneſs; and that without intermiſſion, or end, or eaſe, or patience to indure it.</p>
            <p>O that I could give you but a glimps of it! that you did but ſee it, to the end you might never feel it; that ſo you might be won, if not out of faith,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:151474:23"/>yet out of feare: for certainly this were the hopefulleſt meanes of preventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for though divers Theeves have robbed Paſſengers within ſight of the <hi>Gallowes:</hi> yet if a ſinner could ſee but one glimps of Hell, or be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to looke one moment into that fiery lake, he would rather chuſe to dye ten thouſand deaths, then commit one ſinne. And indeed therefore are we diſſolute, becauſe we do not think what a judgement there is after our diſſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe we make it the leaſt, and laſt thing we think on. Something you have heard of it, but alas I may as well with a Coale paint out the Sunne in his ſplendor; as with my pen, or tongue expreſs the joyes of Heaven (which they willingly part withall) or thoſe torments of Hell (which they ſtrive to purchaſe:) for as one ſaid, that nothing but the eloquence of <hi>Tully,</hi> could ſufficiently ſet forth <hi>Tullies</hi> eloquence: ſo none can expreſſe thoſe everlaſting torments, but he that is from everlaſting to everlaſting. And ſhould either man or Angell goe about the worke, when (with that Philoſopher) he had taken a ſevennights time to conſider of it; he might aske a fortnight more, and at the fortnights end, a month more; and be at his wits end at the worlds end, before he could make a ſatisfying anſwer, other then his was, that the longer he thought of it, the more difficult hee found it. Alas the pain of the body, is but the body of paine; the anguiſh of the ſoule, is the ſoule of anguiſh.</p>
            <p>But to be everlaſtingly in hel, to lye for ever in a bed of quenchleſs flames, is not all: for as thy ſinnes have exceeded, ſo ſhall thy ſufferings exceed. As thou haſt had a double portion of ſinne, to other men here, ſo thou ſhalt have a double portion of torment to them hereafter. The number and meaſure of Torments, ſhall be according to the multitude and magnitude of offences: mighty ſinners ſhall be mightily puniſhed. For <hi>God will reward every man according to his workes, Rev.</hi> 20.12, 13. and 22.12. As our workes are better or worſe; ſo ſhall our joyes in heaven, our paines in hell be more or leſſe. As every one hath beene more wicked, ſo he ſhall bee more wretched. <hi>Capernaum</hi> exceeding <hi>Sodome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> in ſin, ſhall feel alſo an exceſs of puniſhment. And <hi>the wilfull ſervant ſhall receive more ſtripes then the ignorant,</hi> Luke 12.47, 48. Matth. 10 15. Which being ſo, <hi>viz.</hi> that every man ſhall be puniſhed according to merit; what will become of thee? ſurely thy ſinnes are ſo prodigious, that they ſcorne any proportion, under a whole volume of plagues. If thou wilt ſee the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar circumſtances, which greaten, aggravate, and adde weight to thy ſinnes, and make them above meaſure ſinfull; turne to pag. 465. in the <hi>Drunkards Character,</hi> and read to the 142 Section. Or in caſe thou objecteſt, that God is mercifull, and that the Theefe was heard by our Saviour at the laſt houre; read the anſwer to that Plea, from pag. 542. to the 154. Secti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for I cannot ſtand upon them here.</p>
            <p>Neither let drunkards ever hope to eſcape this puniſhment, except in due time they forſake this ſinne; for if every tranſgreſſion without repentance, deſerves the wages of <hi>death</hi> eternall, as a juſt recompence of reward, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.23. how much more this accurſed, and damnable ſinne of
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151474:23"/>drunkenneſs? which both cauſeth, and is attended upon, by almoſt all other ſins, ashath beene proved.</p>
            <p>§ 36. And yet if thou canſt after all this, but truly repent, and lay hold upon Chriſt by a lively faith; which ever manifeſteth it ſelfe by the fruits of a godly life and converſation: know withall that though thy ſinnes have been never ſo many for multitude, never ſo great for magnitude; God is very ready to forgive them; and this I can aſſure thee of; yea I can ſhew thee thy pardon from the great King of <hi>Heaven</hi> for al that is paſt: the Tenure whereof is, <hi>Let the wick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d forſake his wayes, and the unrighteous his own imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, and turn to the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, for he will aboundantly pardon,</hi> Iſa. 55.7. And that we ſhould not doubt of this, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubles the promiſe, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18. and confirmes the ſame with an oath, chap. 33.11. Yea ſinnes upon repentance, are ſo remitted, as if they had never been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ommitted; <hi>I have put away thy tranſgreſſion as a cloud, and thy ſinnes as a miſt.</hi> Eſay 44.22. and what by corruption hath been done, by repentance is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, as aboundance of examples witneſs. He pardoned <hi>Davids</hi> adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, <hi>Solomons</hi> Idolatry, <hi>Peters</hi> Apoſtaſie; <hi>Paul</hi> did not onely deny Chriſt, but perſecuted him in his members as thou doſt; yet he obtained mercy up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his repentance. Yea amongſt the worſt of Gods enemies, ſome are ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled out for mercy; witneſs <hi>Manaſſes, Mary Magdalen,</hi> the <hi>Theefe,</hi> &amp;c. many of the Jewes did not onely <hi>deny Chriſt, the holy one and the juſt,</hi> but crucified him: yet were they pricked in heart at <hi>Peters</hi> Sermon, <hi>gladly received the word, and were baptized,</hi> Acts 2.41.</p>
            <p>Yea I can ſhew thee this very caſe in a preſident, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10, 11. where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e read of certain <hi>Corinthians,</hi> that had been given to this ſin of drunkennes: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho upon their repentance, were both <hi>waſhed, ſanctified,</hi> and <hi>juſtified.</hi> And <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi> tels of one, that being a ſpectacle of drunkenneſs; proved after his converſion, a patterne of ſobriety. Yea know this, that Gods mercy is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thy ſinne, what ever it be: thou canſt not be ſo infinite in ſinning, as he is infinite in pardoning if thou repent. Let us change our ſinnes, and God will change his ſentence. The ſeed of the <hi>Woman,</hi> is able to bruiſe this <hi>Serpents</hi> head. Wherefore if you preferre not <hi>hell</hi> to <hi>heaven;</hi> abandon this vice.</p>
            <p>But withall know, that if it ſhall come to paſs, that the drunkard (when he heareth the words of this curſe, namely theſe threatnings before rehearſed) ſhall <hi>Pharaoh</hi>-like harden his heart, and bleſs himſelfe in his wickedneſs, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>I ſhall have peace, although I walke according to the ſtubbornneſſe of mine owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eart; ſo adding drunkenneſſe to thirſt: the Lord will not be mercifull to that man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut then his wrath and jealouſie ſhall ſmoak againſt him; and every curſe that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritten in his law ſhall light upon him; and the Lord ſhall put out his name from under heaven;</hi> as himſelfe ſpeakes <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.19, 20. which chapter, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the former, I wiſh thee to read, if thou wilt know thy ſelfe, and fore-know thy judgment.</p>
            <p>§ 37. But will ſome <hi>Titormus</hi> ſay, being it may be ſtronger to drinke, and aller to tiple, then <hi>Milo</hi> himſelfe was to eate; who devoured a whole
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151474:24"/>Oxe at a meale, as Poets pretend) I was never ſo gone yet, but I knew th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way home, I could tell what I did, what I ſaid, &amp;c. Yea no man ever ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> me ſo much as wheele in the ſtreets; I am therefore no drunkard, neither d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe threats appertaine to me.</p>
            <p>To whom I anſwer; Perhaps thou art no drunkard in thine owne, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> worlds account; but in Gods account, (whoſe Law extends even to the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and affections, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28.) he is one <hi>that is mighty to drink wine, and of ſtrengt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to pour down ſtrong drink.</hi> Eſay 5.22. He that goes often to the drinke, or tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tarriteth too long as it; <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.30. He that will be drawn to the Tavern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or Alehouſe by every idle ſolicitor, and there be detained whole houres i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> drinking againſt his <hi>ſtomach</hi> and conſtitution of body, againſt his <hi>judge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, the checkes of his owne conſcience, the motions of Gods ſpirit, the ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>neſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> dehortation of his godly friends,</hi> and many woes to the contrary: to the <hi>ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his mony, waſting of his pretious time, neglect of his calling, abuſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the creatures,</hi> (which thouſands better then he want) <hi>wounding of his go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> name, impairing of his health, prejudice of his peace, diſcredit of the Goſpell, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> profeſſors ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>of; the ſtumbling of weak ones, the incouraging of indifferent and unreſolved ones; the fore-ſtaling,</hi> and <hi>hardning of his aſſociates,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>enemies</hi> who know, or heare of it. Briefly, he that drinkes more fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>luſt,</hi> or <hi>pride,</hi> or <hi>covetouſneſſe,</hi> or <hi>feare,</hi> or <hi>good fellowſhip,</hi> or to drive awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>time,</hi> or to ſtill <hi>conſcience,</hi> then for <hi>thirſt,</hi> is a drunkard in <hi>Solomons</hi> dialect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hee is the party to whom thoſe many Woes before rehearſed do belong. Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> drinke is not onely abuſed, when it turnes up a mans heeles, and makes th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> houſe turne round: but when it ſteales away the affections ſo farre, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a man can neither buy, nor ſell, nor meet any friend, or cuſtomer, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtraight to the Taverne, or Alehouſe. Perhaps ſixe times in a day, as is th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> common but baſe cuſtome of moſt Tradeſ-men. And what ever they think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if I have any skill in ſcripture, they are to bee ranked with drunkards. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for thoſe that truely feare God, though they may uſe their Chriſtian liberty, and ſometimes drinke a little for delight; yet ordinarily they drinke a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> other creatures drinke, only to ſatisfie and quench their thirſt. Nor can thoſe formall and titular Chriſtians deny, but in caſes of this nature, things are rather meaſured by the intention, and affection of the doer, then by the iſſue and event. And why ſhould not a man bee deemed a drunkard for his immoderate, and inordinate affection to drinke or drunken Company; as well as an adulterer for the like affection to his neighbours wife, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.28? And ſo much of the reward and puniſhment of this ſin.</p>
            <p>§ 38. I ſhould now proceed to the remedies, at leaſt if there were hope of reclaiming them; but to ſpeake ingenuouſly, I never intended it for their ſakes; as conſidering that habituated drunkards, will be ſure to turne their backs upon this bright ſhining truth, <hi>Jer.</hi> 38.15 Sore <hi>eyes</hi> cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the light of the Sunne; nor <hi>Bankrupts,</hi> of their Counting bookes; nor deformed <hi>faces,</hi> of the Looking-glaſs, as our Saviour ſhewes, <hi>John</hi> 3.19, 20, 21.</p>
            <p>Neither had Satan any braines, if he ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſuffer them. A <hi>Faulkner,</hi> you
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:151474:24"/>know, will carry divers Hawkes hooded quietly; which he could not do if they had the uſe of their ſight; or admit they ſhould read it, I have not the leaſt hope of their yeelding: for theſe lines to them, would be but as ſo many characters written in the water, which leave no impreſſion behinde them, <hi>James</hi> 1.23, 24. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.12, to 16. <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.35. Nor will all the water in the Sea, make one of theſe <hi>Blacke moores</hi> white. The drunkard hath been too long ſicke of this diſeaſe to be recovered. Beſides, it is a ſinne that increaſeth with age; a <hi>Gameſter</hi> will hold out ſo long as his purſe laſts; an <hi>Adulterer</hi> ſo long as his loines laſt; but a <hi>Drunkard</hi> ſo long as his lungs and life laſts. It is like a deſperate <hi>Plague</hi> that knowes no cure. It may be called the <hi>Kings Evill</hi> of the ſoule, that none except God himſelfe can heale: whence <hi>Auguſtine</hi> compares it to the pit of Hell, out of which there is no hope of redemption. I ſpeake of drunkards, not of one drunken; (ſuch who rarely and caſually have <hi>Noah</hi>-like been ſurpriſed, and overtaken at unawares) but once a cuſtom, and ever a neceſſity. As for inſtance, let them be told by any miniſter the hainouſneſs of this ſin, and what a fearfull reckoning of vengeance will come in the end; it is to no more purpoſe, then if he ſhould ſpeake to lifeleſs <hi>ſtones,</hi> or ſenſeleſs <hi>plants,</hi> or witleſs <hi>beaſts.</hi> For they will never fear any thing, till they be in Hell fire. They have no faith in the Scriptures, they will not beleeve what is written, therefore they ſhall feel what is written.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, let God ſend never ſo heavy judgements upon the land; as <hi>Plague, Famine, Warre,</hi> or the like; theſe warped, wicked, wretched men, neither feare, nor ceaſe to rore, drinke, drab, ſweare, &amp;c. ſo little are they moved with Gods diſpleaſure, and thoſe grievous judgements. Yea when the fire of Gods wrath is kindled amongſt us for their ſakes; they do but warm themſelves at the flame, even ſinning ſo much the more freely, and merrily: even living as if they were neither beholding to God, nor afraid of him; both out of his debt and danger. Yea as if the judgement were not onely welcome unto them, but they would fall to courting of their owne deſtruction: as if with <hi>Calanus,</hi> they hated to dye a naturall death.</p>
            <p>Yea thirdly, ſuppoſe the Drunkard hath every day purpoſes to forſake his ſin; ſuppoſe he ſtrives againſt it; yea deteſts and bewailes it in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and others; and thereupon indents with himſelfe and his friends for the relinquiſhing of it: yet let him but meet with a companion that holds but up his finger; he followes him <hi>as a foole to the ſtockes, and as a Oxe to the ſlaughter-houſe:</hi> having no power to withſtand the temptation; but in he goes with him to the tipling houſe, and there he continues as one bewitched, or conjured with a Spell; out of which he returnes not, till he hath emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied his purſe of <hi>money,</hi> his head of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaſon,</hi> and his heart of all his former ſeeming <hi>grace.</hi> O this is a difficult Devil to be caſt out! and I wiſh men would beware of it in time; for when a man is once poſſeſt with this evill ſpirit, a drunken Devill; it is a miracle if ever he become his owne man after. And indeed it is much to be feared, that the Lord hath done by
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:151474:25"/>them, as by <hi>Jeremiah;</hi> he threatneth the Babylonians, even <hi>given them over to a perpetuall drunkenneſſe,</hi> Jer. 51.39. And is it not juſt with God that he who will put out his naturall light, ſhould have his ſpirituall extinguiſhed? he that will deprive himſelfe of reaſon, ſhould loſe alſo the guide, and pilot of reaſon Gods ſpirit, and grace? he that will wittingly and willingly make himſelfe an habitation of uncleane ſpirits, ſhould not diſpoſeſſe them at his pleaſure?</p>
            <p>Alas the fleſh, unto them that ſhall periſh, will be ſtronger then all my reaſons. The ſound of the pot with them, will drowne all reprehenſion, all admonition. They will rather be confounded then reformed; and nothing will confute them, but <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>brimſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All thoſe beaſts which went into the Arke uncleane, came likewiſe out uncleane: and a brute Beaſt is as capable of good counſell, as a drunkard once become a ſcorner: yea as <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeakes, we were as good round a dead man in the eare, as admoniſh a drunkard. And indeed he is dead in ſinne, (onely his ſinne is alive;) and not onely dead as <hi>Jairus</hi> daughter was, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.25. nor onely dead, laid out, and coffin'd, as the Widowes ſone of <hi>Naum</hi> was, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.14. but even dead, coffin'd, and buried, with a <hi>Stone</hi> upon the <hi>Graves</hi> mouth to keep him in, by reaſon of long cuſtome, as <hi>Lazarus</hi> was, <hi>John</hi> 11.39. even till he ſtinkes in the noſtrils of God, and all good men. And what rubbing can fetch heat in ſuch a dead body? as appeares by the exemples of <hi>Pharaod, Exod.</hi> 7. chap. to 14. The <hi>Sodomites, Gen.</hi> 19. <hi>Hazael,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.12, to 16. <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 22.16, to 53. <hi>Balaam, Num.</hi> 22.30. &amp;c. The <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees, Mat.</hi> 27.51, &amp;c. <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.22, &amp;c. Yea to expect that this unmasking their faces, ſhould humble and reclaime them; were to imitate the Foole, that carried his <hi>ſaddle</hi> to ſhame his <hi>horſe;</hi> or to tell them what is denounced in the Word againſt this ſinne, were almoſt as ridiculous, as that Ceremony which the <hi>Mahometans</hi> uſe, of flinging ſtones to <hi>ſtone the Devill</hi> with. Wherefore I have no other meſſage to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver unto ſuch an one, then that which the vigilant Captaine delivered, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with a deaths wound to his ſleeping Watchman, Dead I found thee, and dead I leave thee.</p>
            <p>Onely thou O Father, (to whom nothing is hard) if it be thy good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, (as why not? ſeeing it wil make much for the glory of thy great name, to ſave ſuch a mighty ſinner; who <hi>Manaſſes</hi>-like, hath multiplyed offences above the number of the ſand of the Sea; and is bound downe with many iron bands) ſay unto his ſoule, Live: It is true, thy angry threatning toward ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners is importable; but thy mercifull promiſe, is unmeaſurable, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſearchable: Thou therefore that art able to quicken the dead, and make even of Stones, children to <hi>Abraham,</hi> mollifie theſe ſtony and dead hearts with the bloud of the Lambe; and make of theſe children of the Devill, members of thy ſonne Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>§ 39. But here ſome haſtily, (peradventure over haſtily) will ſay; this is a ſtrange courſe, to diſcourſe againſt drunkenneſs; when you have no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151474:25"/>that drunkards ſhould give it the hearing. For, as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>They that are whole need not the Phyſitian, but they that are ſicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer; what though theſe deafe <hi>Adders</hi> will not be charmed? (as that muſicke loſeth both its ſound and grace, which is beſtowed upon the deafe.) What though none of this herd of habituated drunkards will be cured? yet ſome young ones may be deterred, ſome Novices reclaimed, ſome Parents, Maſters, and Magiſtrates awakened, to prevent and ſuppreſs the ſpreading of this <hi>Gangren:</hi> and we are no leſs commanded to uſed the meanes. I have done it alſo for their ſakes, who are not yet infected with this drunken good fellowſhip, to increaſe their deteſtation of evill company, and that the others purpoſe may be infatuated. For <hi>vices true picture makes us vice deteſt.</hi> And what though every plant that is watered, proveth not fruitfull? yet if God (who it may be hath bidden me ſpeake) but accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany his Word to the hearts of ſome; if but a few, if but one be perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, in ſtead of loving this vice, to hate it; the labour is not in vaine, the gaine of one ſoule, is greater then the Indies.</p>
            <p>Now Phyſitians ſay, if the Diſeaſe be once knowne, the Cure is halfe done. Here you have drunkenneſs diſapparelled of her robes, and her face ſo unvailed, that poſſibly the ſight of it may cauſe ſuch a loathing, and that loathing, ſuch a forſaking; that hundreds of others may both <hi>know, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor,</hi> and <hi>beware</hi> their <hi>allurements;</hi> ſtrive againſt the <hi>ſin,</hi> ſhun all <hi>occaſions</hi> of it, bewaile their <hi>caſes</hi> that are led captive to it; <hi>neglect their cenſures, labour their recovery, and pray for their ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>§ 40. Now if any of them ſhall aske, how they may uſe and apply this remedy for their beſt advantage? I anſwer, upon every occaſion let them examine what the drunkard (herein ſet forth) does; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> do the contrary: for he is the moſt ſober and honeſt man, that reſembles this drunkard leaſt. Do but con this leſſon, 'tis enough. Nevertheleſs, leſt I ſhould imitate thoſe, who kindle a <hi>fire</hi> under green <hi>wood,</hi> and leave it ſo ſoone as it begins to flame; read alſo <hi>Compleat Armour againſt evill Society:</hi> for as in this Treatiſe, I have ſhewed what drunkards do, ſo in that I have ſhewed them, and others what they ſhould do.</p>
            <p>Only I will adde a word of advice; If any would eſcape this ſnare of the Devill, and Drunkards: let them have a ſpeciall care, to refraine the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of this drunken rout, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.20. who not onely make a ſport of drunkenneſs, but delight alſo to make others drunke.</p>
            <p>There are ſome Vices of that nature, that they cannot be vanquiſhed, but by avoiding, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.18. ſuch is this: bid a man conſort a while with Drunkards, and depart from them innocent; you may as well put a match to dry powder, and forbid it to take fire. It is not ſate to commit a little <hi>Wherry</hi> to the Seas violence. A ſtick that hath once been in the fire, will ſoone take fire againe; and corruption, like a candle new put out, is ſoone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ighted againe: if Satan but blow upon it, the owne heat is enough to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame it. It is not ſafe venturing into evill company, in confidence of our owne ſtrength; no more then it is to conſort with Cheaters in hope that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:151474:26"/>they will not conſen us. <hi>They wer emingled among the Heathen</hi> (ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt,) and what followes? <hi>they learned their workes,</hi> Pſal. 106.35. Yea how ſoone was <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe changed, with but coming into the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prieſts Hall? Nor had he ever denied, and forſworne his Maſter, if he had not been in company with Chriſts enemies. Nor had <hi>David</hi> ever ſo diſſembled, if he had not beene among the <hi>Philiſtims.</hi> Which made him ſay, ſo ſoone as he had conſidered it, <hi>Depart from me all yee workers of iniquity, for I will keep the commandements of my God,</hi> Pſal. 119.115. As knowing that the one could not be without the other. And indeed it is rare, if with <hi>Peter</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deny not Chriſt in <hi>Caiaphas</hi> his houſe: with <hi>Solomon</hi> we ſhall finde it hard having the <hi>Aegyptian</hi> without her Idols. Yea how many thouſand of theſe drunkards have confeſt at the Gallowes: I had never come to this, but for evill company which drew me to theſe courſes? And indeed, why do wee pray <hi>not to be led into temptation;</hi> if wee lead our ſelves into temptation? if we will not keep our ſelves from the <hi>occaſion,</hi> God will not keep us from the <hi>ſinne:</hi> and if God do not keep us, wee cannot be kept; wee cannot, we will not chooſe but fall. Wherefore as <hi>Joſeph</hi> no ſooner heard his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris ſay, come let us lye together, but he left her and fled away; ſo if you but heare good fellowes ſay, come let us drinke together, be ſure to leave them, though without taking your leave of them. Satan and his inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments like a <hi>flattering Hoſt,</hi> may promiſe good cheere, but the reckoning payes for all; and he that compares the welcome with the farewell, ſhall finde he had better have faſted; for if we ſwallow the <hi>bait,</hi> the <hi>hooke</hi> will choak us. Wherefore be as wary, and as wife as a <hi>Serpent,</hi> to keep out, or at leaſt to get out of their company; but as innocent as a <hi>Dove</hi> if it be poſſible, while thou art in i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and canſt not chooſe. Remembring alwayes, that they are but the Devils <hi>deputies;</hi> yea <hi>hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne</hi> Devils, as once our Saviour called <hi>Peter</hi> (being inſtrumentall to Satan) Satan himſelfe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.23. Change no words with them, for there is no diſputing with Satan or his Agents; as you may ſee by his ſucceſs in Paradiſe; when he ſo eaſily perſwaded <hi>Eve</hi> by himſelfe, and <hi>Adam</hi> by her; to beleeve what he ſpake, though they had heard <hi>God</hi> himſelf ſay the contrary immediately before. When <hi>Caſtles</hi> once come to a parly, there is great feare they will yeeld, and Gates that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes open, will ſometimes admit an enemy.</p>
            <p>Neither will the complaint of our firſt parents be taken for a good anſwer, or plea another day, it will be fruitleſſe to ſay ſuch and ſuch a friend decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me: <hi>Eve</hi> was perſwaded by the <hi>Serpent</hi> to eat the forbidden fruit, and <hi>Adam</hi> by <hi>Eve;</hi> yet each had a ſeverall curſe; both tempters, and tempted.</p>
            <p>§ 41. Now by obſerving, or not obſerving this rule; it will appeare whether there be any hope of thy holding out, for all depends upon this; yea could the moſt <hi>infatuated, habituated, incorrigible, cauteriſed</hi> drunkard, that is even dead in this ſinne; but forſake his ill company, I ſhould not once doubt of his recovery; for do but drive away theſe uncleane birds from the Carkaſſe, a million to amity, the Lord may be pleaſed to <hi>breath into his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151474:26"/>noſtrils</hi> againe, <hi>the breath of life, and he become a living ſoule.</hi> O that all drunkards were driven to the <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> there to drinke water and worke, untill ſome divine <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> could procure them their reaſon, and perſwade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem once againe to become men, ſober men, yea ſound Chriſtians: ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould our Nation flouriſh againe, and be better provided with honeſt men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or places of truſt, both in Church and State, then now it is, where ſo few have publick ſpirits, and prove faithful. And what juſterpuniſhment can there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e deviſed, then that they ſhall be debarred both of the bloud of the Grape, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the ſpirit of Barley; for conſuming the Countries fat? Were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>leare <hi>Rocke-water</hi> good enough for ſuch <hi>Gormondizers?</hi> Or if authority <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hinkes not this fit; I could wiſh there were Peſthouſes provided for them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n all places, as there are for infected perſons. Or that they were put by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hemſelves in ſome City, (if any were big enough to receive them all) as <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> built a City of purpoſe; and peopled it with the moſt wicked, graceleſs, and irregular perſons of all his ſubjects; and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing ſo done, called it <hi>Poneropolis,</hi> that is, the <hi>City of wicked perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And certainely if it were well conſidered, how many of theſe <hi>Brokers of cillany,</hi> which live only upon the ſpoiles of young hopes, every populous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lace affords: and what evill they do by their <hi>ſeducing</hi> ſome, and giving ill <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xamples</hi> to others, by devouring the good <hi>Creatures</hi> of God which they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er ſweat for, by <hi>diſturbing</hi> the peace of Church and Common-wealth, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ulling downe heavy judgements upon the <hi>Land,</hi> and conſidering the little good they doe (being as ſo many looſe <hi>Teeth</hi> in the mandable of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, which were better out then in) and what ſmall hope there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f their amendment, if any at all: the like meanes of prevention would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e thought profitable for our times. I do not wiſh them ſtoned to death, as God commanded ſuch rioters, and drunkards to be, under the <hi>Law, Deut.</hi> 21.20, 21. Nor <hi>bamſhed the Land,</hi> as the Romans did all vitious, and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uptuous perſons, that the reſt might not be endangered. And <hi>Lycurgus</hi> all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nventers of new faſhions, leſt theſe things ſhould effeminate all their young men: for then I feare the land would be much unpeopled. And ſo much for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he avoiding of drunken company.</p>
            <p>§ 42. Secondly, be carefull to abſtain from drinking places, which are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en the nurſeries of all riot, exceſs, and idleneſs; making our land another <hi>Sodome,</hi> and furniſhing yearly our Jails, and Gallowſes. Far be it from me to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lame a good calling, to accuſe the innocent in that calling; I know the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath many in the world in theſe houſes; but ſure I am, too many of them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re even the <hi>dennes,</hi> and <hi>ſhops,</hi> yea the <hi>thrones</hi> of Satan; very ſinkes of ſin, which like ſo many common-ſhoares, or receptacles, refuſe not to welcome, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd incourage any in the moſt loathſome pollutions they are able to invent, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd put in practice.</p>
            <p>Who if there were any hope of prevailing, would be minded of their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>edneſs, in entertaining into their houſes, encouraging, and complying with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe <hi>Traitors</hi> againſt God; and of their danger in ſuffering ſo much im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iety, to reſt within their Gates. For if one ſinne of <hi>Theft,</hi> or of <hi>perjury</hi> is
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:151474:27"/>enough to rot the <hi>Rafters,</hi> to <hi>grinde</hi> the <hi>ſtones,</hi> to levell the <hi>wals,</hi> and <hi>roofe</hi> of any houſe, with the ground, as is laid down <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.4. what are the oathes, the lyes, the thefts, the whoredomes, the murthers, the numberleſs, and nameleſs abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, that are committed there? But ſhould I ſpeake to theſe, I ſhould but ſpeed as <hi>Paul</hi> at <hi>Epheſus;</hi> I ſhould be cryed downe with <hi>Great is Diana,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome one <hi>Demetrius had told the reſt of this occupation, Sirs, ye know that by this craft we have our wealth.</hi> Surely if feare of having their <hi>Signes</hi> pulled downe, their <hi>licenſes</hi> called in, &amp;c. cannot prevaile, it little bootes me to ſpeake.</p>
            <p>§ 43. Only to you <hi>Churchwardens, Conſtables,</hi> and other Officers, that love the Lord, the Church, the State, your ſelves, and people; <hi>Help the Lord, the King and his Lawes, againſt this mighty ſinne;</hi> preſent it, indict it, ſmite it, every one ſhoot at it as a common enemy, do what you can to ſuppreſs and prevent it.</p>
            <p>Tell me not he is a friend, a gentleman, ſuch an ones kinſman that offends, for he is better, and greater, and nearer to you, that is offended. Learne to feare, to love, and obey your Maker, and Saviour, your Soveraigne and Protector. Yea learne this <hi>Norman</hi> diſtinction; when <hi>William</hi> the firſt, cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured one that was both <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Bajeux,</hi> and <hi>Earle</hi> of <hi>Kent;</hi> his Apology to the plaintife popeling was, that he meddled not with the Biſhop, but the Earle do you the like, let the gentleman eſcape, but ſtock the drunkard; med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle not with your friend, and kinſman, but for all that pay the drunkard, and make his Hoſt pay that ſuffers him to be drunke. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if you do not to your power, you ſhall have <hi>Ahabs</hi> wages, his faults ſhall be beaten upon your backs. 1 <hi>King.</hi> 20.42.</p>
            <p>§ 44. But moſt of all are they to be deſired, who are within the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Peace in Gods name, whoſe ſervants they profeſſe themſelves to be, to remember <hi>him, themſelves,</hi> their <hi>country,</hi> their <hi>oathes,</hi> and to bend their ſtrength and power againſt this many-headed Monſter; that they will purge their Country, much more their owne houſes, of this pernicious and vipe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous brood. Yea if there be any love of God, any hatred of ſinne, any zeal, any courage, any conſcience of an oath: away with drunkenneſſe out of your Houſes, Townes, Liberties; balk none, beare with none that offend: ſay they be poore in whoſe houſes the ſinne is practiſed; it is better one or two ſhould loſe their gaine, then Townes of men ſhould loſe their wits, their wealths, their ſoules. O beloved, did you heare, and ſee, and ſmell, and know, what is done in ſome one <hi>Taverne,</hi> or <hi>Alehouſe</hi> (hell-houſe I might call it) in this land; you would wonder that the earth could bear the houſe, or the Sunne endure to looke upon it. But alas how many of theſe Houſes be there in ſome one Towne? how many of theſe Townes in ſome one Shire, and ſo upward?</p>
            <p>You often complaine of <hi>Baſtardies, Sheep ſtealers, robbers, quarrellers,</hi> and the like, will you be eaſed of theſe diſeaſes? beleeve it, theſe gather into the Alehouſe, as the humours do into the ſtomach againſt an <hi>Ague fit;</hi> take them there, drive them thence, with ſome ſtrong phyſick; and you heale our land at once of infinite diſtempers.</p>
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:151474:27"/>
            <p>Here I might alſo minde you, of moſt priſons: <hi>Juſt Lot was vexed with the uncleanly converſation of his wicked neighbours; Sodome was worſe then a Jaile, to his righteous ſoule;</hi> and report lyes, if our Jailes be not much like to <hi>Sodome;</hi> the very dens of miſchiefe, the ſchooles of wickedneſs; a malefactor, or broken Shop-keeper, learnes more villany there, then ever he knew before. Drunkenneſſe, and blaſphemy, uſurpe the places of <hi>Mortification</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> though moſt unfit it ſhould be ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Such as would know more of this, and other ſubjects more ſerious; let them read</hi> Sinne Stigmatized, <hi>from which I have pluckt this, as a</hi> Bunch of Grapes <hi>from a large</hi> Vine.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:28"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Spartans</hi> and <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> uſed to ſhew their Slaves in their drunkenneſs unto their children, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that their ugly deformity both in body and minde, would be an effectual argument to make them loath this vice, which even at the firſt view ſeemed ſo horrid. The <hi>Perſians</hi> and <hi>Parthians</hi> alſo, to the ſame end kept alwayes in their houſes the like ugly, and deformed deſcriptions lively painted out; and found it by experience, the moſt operative and effectuall courſe to keep theirs from ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. And nothing, as <hi>Anacharſis</hi> holds, will ſooner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime a man from Drunkenneſſe, then the <hi>ſeeing</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring</hi> of a drunkards odious condition, and beaſtly behaviour.</p>
            <p>Would we then that are Chriſtians have our children and ſervants decline this <hi>bewitching, beſotting, infectious,</hi> and <hi>incurable ſinne;</hi> this <hi>waſtefull, inſatiable, unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, unnaturall ſinne;</hi> this <hi>baſe, brutiſh, atheiſticall, exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable, prodigious,</hi> and <hi>infernall ſinne;</hi> this <hi>tranſcendent ſin,</hi> which is the cauſe of all other <hi>ſins;</hi> yea a confluence or collection of every <hi>ſinne;</hi> even turning a man wholly into <hi>ſinne:</hi> this ſinne that is the Funerall of all a mans good parts, and indiſpoſeth him to all grace and godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; yea to all the means thereof? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> uſe we them, and that often, to read over in our families, this <hi>deſcription of a drunkard:</hi> and for ought we know, ours and after ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerations, may by Gods bleſſing, be leſs inamored with this <hi>loathſome, and worſe then beaſtly abomination.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>
               <hi>Imprimatur</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>John Downam.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:151474:28"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
